<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The saints legacies: or, A collection of certaine promises out of the word of God Collected for private use, but published for the comfort of Gods people: by Anne Phoenix.</title>
            <title>Collection of certaine promises out of the word of God.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1633</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 149 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 143 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A72054</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10635.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S124923</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99898928</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99898928</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150899</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A72054)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150899)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1986:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The saints legacies: or, A collection of certaine promises out of the word of God Collected for private use, but published for the comfort of Gods people: by Anne Phoenix.</title>
                  <title>Collection of certaine promises out of the word of God.</title>
                  <author>Fawkner, Antony, b. 1601 or 2, attributed name.</author>
                  <author>Farindon, Anthony, 1598-1658, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The third edition, corrected and amended.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[60], 203, [17] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by M. F[lesher]. for R. Roystone in Ivy-Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1633.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Anne Phoenix is a pseudonym; previous editions signed: A.F., possibly Antony Fawkner or Anthony Farindon--STC.</note>
                  <note>Originally published in 1629 as: A collection of certaine promises out of the word of God.</note>
                  <note>Includes table of contents.</note>
                  <note>final leaf missing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library, London, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Meditations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Word of God (Theology) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150899:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Saints Legacies:</hi> OR, A COLLECTION of certaine PROMISES out of the word of God.</p>
            <p>Collected for private uſe, but publiſhed for the comfort of Gods people: <hi>By</hi> ANNE PHOENIX.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Beleeve the Promiſes: ſo ſhall you proſper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By beleeving and applying the Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, we come to participate of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Nature. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. Whereby are given unto us exceeding great and precious Promiſes, that by theſe we might be partakers of the divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p>The third Edition, corrected and amended.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>M. F.</hi> for <hi>R. Royſtone</hi> in Ivy-Lane. 1633.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:150899:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150899:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150899:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150899:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:150899:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150899:4"/>
            <head>TO THE HAP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PIE SOCIETIE of all true Beleevers.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gracious Beleevers,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">K</seg>Nowing you to bee the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heires of thoſe rich and precious promiſes, which it hath pleaſed our gracious Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther freely to give unto his freely beloved Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren:
<pb facs="tcp:150899:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>I have preſumed without your knowledge, to bequeath unto you a fatherleſs childe brought forth into the world with out the pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts knowledg, hoping you will not be unwilling to let it paſſe under your favourable protection. For the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject matter of it, it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry beautifull, and of ſuch uſe, as no child of God can paſſe to Heaven without it, and in that regard, it ſhalbe no ſhame unto you
<pb facs="tcp:150899:5"/>whom the Lord hath ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured with the grace of beleeving, to accept of this ſmall treatiſe from one that deſires your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpering in your ſoules &amp; bodies. There is no ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh in this that I dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate unto you, but ſuch as came by the hands of the unskilfull bringer forth of it, which onely minded their own good in it. And weighing daily the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of it, and the ſweet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing ſtrength which
<pb facs="tcp:150899:6"/>flowed from it, for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercomming of thoſe three deadly enemies, the Devil, Sinne, and the World, they deſired that God would bee pleaſed to move the mindes of ſome of his moſt skilful work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, to put to their hands to frame a more perfect worke upon ſo perfect a ſubject, and to give a more comely forme, to this ſo beautifull a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and till then they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to ſmother in
<pb facs="tcp:150899:6"/>their boſomes the beauty of this, rather then to bring it forth with the blemiſhes of their unskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe. But the good that may bee gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by it being unut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terable, I hope grace in the hearts of Gods people will cauſe them, like the Bee, ſucke out the ſweet and nouriſhing vertue of theſe fragrant flowers, that growe here &amp; there in the garden of Gods word, and not with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content
<pb facs="tcp:150899:7"/>to caſt away this pleaſant poſie, gathered out of the celeſtiall <hi>Eden</hi> of the ſacred Scriptures, becauſe an unskilfull hand, and indeed unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie, hath bound them up together, not ſo orderly as might pleaſe the curious eye of man, no nor their owne, neither was it their ayme ſo to doe. If any gaine any good by it, the gatherer of theſe ſweet flowers together, neither deſerves nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires
<pb facs="tcp:150899:7"/>thankes, for they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended it to none but to themſelves, and ſome pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate friends, whoſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie wrung ſome copies from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; now without their conſent have publiſhed it. And now ſince it is publiſhed and cannot bee ſtopped, the Lord cauſe it to work in all his, according to that which he hath given the promiſes for to work in the hearts of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, even to make them
<pb facs="tcp:150899:8"/>partakers of the divine nature. <hi>2. Pet. 1.4.</hi> and as a meanes to make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to take everie day a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle poſie from the reſt, one of the promiſes ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together, &amp; apply it to thy ſelf, ſee how thou ſtandeſt in need of it, and every word in it, &amp; then apply it to thy ſelfe by faith, &amp; let it ſtirre thee up to goe to God in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er for the accompliſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of them unto thee, then wait in the diligent uſe
<pb facs="tcp:150899:8"/>of all meanes for the gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of them, &amp; you ſhal finde God not onely ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king you heires of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, but you ſhalbe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable poſſeſſours of thoſe many good things which God hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to beleevers. The more you meditate and the oftner you pray up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, the more good will you ſee in them, and finde flow from them. I ſay no more, but I doubt not, but your experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb facs="tcp:150899:9"/>of good by theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes wil be more then I can make known unto you I deſire the God of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, our louing father, in our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, in whom all the promiſes are Yea and Amen, to make you daily finde ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimentally, the truth of al his gracious promiſes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:150899:9"/>
            <head>TO THE SAME Right Honourable and happie Societie of all true Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers militant in England: A Friend to you, and the Author, wiſheth fulneſſe of grace, peace, and heavenly comfort, certaine aſſurance; ſealed evidence, and ſeaſonable entrance into, and poſſeſſion of the celeſtiall, promiſed, incorruptible, undefiled and never fading in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eloved Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, both you and I, are infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely
<pb facs="tcp:150899:10"/>beholden to our everliving Father, who hath made his will and given all us his children great wealth, rich portions, and large Legacies. Now, in preſent poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, Graces, and comforts, in unſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken expectation and aſſured reverſion, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and eternall glory. Wee are greatly beholding to <hi>Iehova,</hi> for his will damnato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,
<pb facs="tcp:150899:10"/>directorie, horta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie, correctorie, but moſt of all for his will conſolatorie, in which, he ſalves all our ſores, phyſicks all our ſickneſſes, medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines al our maladies,<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 103.4.</note> heales all our diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and crownes us with loving kindnes and tender mercies? And ſurely wee are all of us much behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the holy Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of this ſweet
<pb facs="tcp:150899:11"/>(though little) booke, who hath ſo piouſly, painefully, and profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably peruſed the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly will of our heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father, and wiſely ſought and found out and put into our handes, the ſpirituall portion, and ſoule-le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacies, given and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queathed unto us by our beſt friend, many of which, moſt of us ſcarce knew of, few ſought and ſued for
<pb facs="tcp:150899:11"/>them, and very few comfortably enjoyed and wiſely and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently uſed, to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours glory and their owne good. Careleſſe children, come often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to be beholding unto their more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full brethren and thri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving friends, who ſave all they have, ſue for all that is promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and ſeeke for all they heare of: ſo is it here, we careleſs, neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent,
<pb facs="tcp:150899:12"/>poore and ill thriven Chriſtians, muſt bee beholding to this carefull, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, rich and well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thriven author, who obeyes <hi>Pauls</hi> counſell<note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 12 31.</note>1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12 31. Couets earneſtly the beſt gifts and will not ſuffer the heavenly Father, to purſe and keep a pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie that is due, to with-hold grace or comfort (which hee hath promiſed) in
<pb facs="tcp:150899:12"/>whole, or degree, but he ſhall heare of his promiſe, and if hee do not preſently ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill according to cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, a petition is ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily drawne, to bee preferred in the court of heaven, and an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate prepared leſus Chriſt the righteous.<note n="c" place="margin">1 Ioh. 2.1</note>1 <hi>Iohn.</hi> 2.1. Suite (by prayer) begun, and in an eager purſuite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, till the thing promiſed bee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:150899:13"/>
            <p> This little booke, &amp; private practice of the author (who hath ſued for all theſe Legacies, and in ſome good meaſure hath attained the ſame, and thereby is become ſpiritually rich) will ſufficiently proove what I have ſpoken. VVee are much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden to this au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, for letting us ſee our portion and lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies
<pb facs="tcp:150899:13"/>in our fathers wil and ſetting us a work both by penne and practiſe to ſue for the ſame.</p>
            <p>The volume is lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, but the vertue contained in the ſame is great. The booke is extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie, being altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for application and practiſe. The ſcope and drift of it is, to furniſh beleevers with abundance of
<pb facs="tcp:150899:14"/>good; to free them from all ſins inward, outward, ſecret, and open; To fill them with all graces in life, power, and exerciſe; To bring them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in, and ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deliverance from, all their troubles; To draw downe upon their ſoules &amp; bodies abundance of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of all ſorts and natures: to give them full aſſurance of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb facs="tcp:150899:14"/>and ſeaſonable entrance into glory, and to give them faſt hold of heaven.</p>
            <p>There are many, I know, that will little regard it: the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane perſon wil not like it, for it is full of holineſſe: the carnall proteſtant will not diſcerne of it, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh it, for it is ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: the diſſembling hypocrite wil not wel approve of it, for it
<pb facs="tcp:150899:15"/>will rob him of his <hi>Rimmon</hi> ſlay his M<hi rend="sup">rs.</hi>, his <hi>Delilah,</hi> his <hi>Hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dias,</hi> his daling ſinne, it will tell him, if he applyes promiſes, hee muſt keepe the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, obey praecept, and put every iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie though never ſo pleaſurable or profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble far way from his Tabernacles. But the honeſt hearted and ſinceere beleever will approve of it, prize it,
<pb facs="tcp:150899:15"/>uſe it, and profit by it.</p>
            <p>And not to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie, as one deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to make it more vendible and ſailable (for neither I, nor its author (God is wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) ayme at any ſuch thing, but at the ſpiritual good of their ſoules unto whom it ſhall come) this little booke, like a well fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led little Apothecaries
<pb facs="tcp:150899:16"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:150899:16"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:150899:17"/>ſhop, containes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it heavenly receipts of all ſorts, wholſome phyſick of every kind for expelling and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all ſorts of diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and ſickneſſes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident to Saints, and for the corroborating and ſtrengthning of new nature, and for keeping the ſpirituall man in good health, luſtie and ſtrong, able for Gods ſervice,<note n="d" place="margin">Phil. 2.12.</note> &amp; for working out his
<pb facs="tcp:150899:17"/>owne ſalvation with feare and trembling. What here I ſpeak un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one beleever, I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for all.</p>
            <p>Hath ſin, that dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly poyſon infected thee? Lo here in this little booke an Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dote, a preſervative which will extract and expell this poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Hath this ſerpent ſo fierie ſtung thee?<note n="e" place="margin">Numb. 21.8.</note> Lo here the <hi>Braſen Serpent</hi> upon the pole.
<pb facs="tcp:150899:18"/>Hath it beggered and undone thee?<note place="margin">Ioh. 3.14, 15.</note> Behold a way in this booke, how thou maiſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come rich. Doth it dayly trouble thee, will it needs tyranize and dominere over thee? This little book will learne thee to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe this Tyrant,<note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 6.14.</note> and tell thee hee ſhall not haue dominion and Lordſhip over thee. Hath it ſtricken thee dead? Lo here meanes
<pb facs="tcp:150899:18"/>of reviving and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>living thee, to an hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie life of grace. Doth it threaten thy ruine? Lo here phyſicke for thy feares,<note n="g" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.35.</note> death hath loſt its ſting, ſinne is deſtroyed, death ſhall fully and finally free thee from it. Art thou hunted like a poore lambe by the helliſh devouring Lion, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, and chaſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this infernal dog, like a ſilly Deere, in
<pb facs="tcp:150899:19"/>temptations? Lo here a thicket, a ſhelter, a ſhepheard, under which thou mayeſt repoſe and reſt thy ſelfe in ſafetie. Art thou overcome with his wilie ſtratagems? Lo here wiſedome. Art thou beaten down with his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er? Lo here ſtrength. Feareſt thou the fierie darts of this evill one? Lo here a little houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of targets, ſheilds
<pb facs="tcp:150899:19"/>and buklers,(<note n="h" place="margin">Epheſ. 6.16.</note> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes applyed by faith) which will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel and quench them.<note n="i" place="margin">Iob. 6.4.</note> Do Gods terrours ſet themſelves in array againſt thee? are Gods arrowes in thee? doth his flaming wrath burne in thy boſome, and is likely to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume thee? Lo ſtreames of mercy &amp; grace from a refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fountaine, fluent in the pipes of the
<pb facs="tcp:150899:20"/>promiſes; by thy hand of faith turn the cock, and the coole water of Gods grace &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy ſhall flow forth upon thy ſoule, and allay its burning heat, and ſcorching infla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations. Doth the wilie world ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to intangle and inveagle thee by its lures and ſnares? Lo here liberty, freedome better things propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and promiſed,
<pb facs="tcp:150899:20"/>which beleevers doe for the preſent in ſome meaſure enjoy, and ſhall have a moſt certaine and full poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of afterwards. Wanteſt thou Grace, comfort, deliverance, bleſſing, or any good thing? Behold here thou mayeſt have them, to the great joy of theine heart, and content of thy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</p>
            <p>Set faith a worke
<pb facs="tcp:150899:21"/>to draw out what thou wanteſt, &amp; thou ſhalt have it. Sucke theſe ſweet and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly breaſts of God by the mouth of thy faith; open theſe pipes and veines of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, which run ſo full of mercy, grace, truth, comfort, joy &amp; peace, for every beele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, by faith; and thou ſhalt be ſatiate with every good thing.</p>
            <p>Leſt I ſhold make
<pb facs="tcp:150899:21"/>too great a porch for this little houſe, and too great gates for this little citie, I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, with an exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to all my belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved brethren and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, which are belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, to perfect their faith by application of the promiſes, both of theſe in this ſweet little booke, and of all others, contained in the Old and New Teſtament.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:150899:22"/>
            <p> Suffer not GODS promiſes (as I may ſo ſay) to milke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, doe you draw them, let not good reſt with God, which you may have, by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving and begging, to your great comfort and inriching, but take Gods commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities off his hand, trade with that weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Merchant in the farre Countrey, the Lord Ieſus in heaven,
<pb facs="tcp:150899:22"/>for his rich commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities of graces and comforts, and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous hopes untill you be rich and wealthy, and for this purpoſe cauſe thoſe two good factours, <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Prayer,</hi> founded upon and quickned &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous promiſes, alway to trade for you in heaven, untill you come thither your ſelves. I would deſire
<pb facs="tcp:150899:23"/>all beleevers to make this their pocket book that it may ſollicite and wooe them to prayer, make ſolid &amp; firme their faith, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe their graces, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, and heavenly hopes, prepare them for induring the ſtormes of trouble &amp; tempeſts of temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and may incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage them in holy weldoing and chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian perſeverance un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:150899:23"/>the end.<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heh.</hi> 6.12</note> Now bretheren; my hearts deſire is, that yee bee not ſlothfull, but fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of them, who through faith and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience inherit the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</p>
            <p>That you may bee inheritours of them, it ſhalbe my daily prayer unto the Lord my God, to beſtow upon your heartes to uſe all good meanes, for the attaining of
<pb facs="tcp:150899:24"/>the good, in theſe &amp; other promiſes of God unto his people. That he would teach and enable you to meditate upon them diligently day and night, to beleeve the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> firmly, to apply the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeverally, particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, perſonally, to ſue for them earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by prayer conſtant and fervent, to wait for their promiſed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment by pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,
<pb facs="tcp:150899:24"/>that ſo you may enjoy the good of them here &amp; here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, which God in mercie grant unto mee, and alſo you. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:150899:25"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150899:25"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>An which at the beginning was created happy,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.26.</note> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.12.</note> having now loſt God and his image,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.2.3.</note> is of all earthly creatures become moſt miſerable, no leſſe then a ſlave of the Devill, a child of wrath, and an heire of eternall damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4</note> This is not the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of a few onely, but of all man-kinde out of Chriſt; for we are all by nature under the curſe.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:150899:26"/>The beſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.3.</note> before their converſion, were by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture children of wrath, even as others: for every womans child did fall equally in <hi>Adam:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12.</note> hence it comes to paſſe, that no man by nature is now in better eſteem with God then other. <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel</hi> as children of the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> onely were equally miſerable; the like may be ſaid of us all,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.9.</note> for both Jewes and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles are come under ſin. And as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 14.3.</note> Wee are all gone out of the way, wee are altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther become filthy, there is none righteous, no not
<pb facs="tcp:150899:26"/>one. Oh that men and women had their eyes enlightned, and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments convinced of that woefull plight in which naturally they are! Oh! were their hearts thor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly loaden therewith, ſurely they would not long content themſelves therein. The truth is,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Iohn.</hi> 5.19.</note> moſt in the world are ſpiritually blinde,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.</note> and cannot diſcerne their owne miſerie;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually dead too, &amp; can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee affected with it: The Holy Ghoſt ſaith thus of them;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.1 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 19.</note> 
               <hi>They walke in the vanity of their mind, having their underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:150899:27"/>darkned, and are ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers from the life of God, through the ignorance which is in them, becauſe of the hardnes of their hearts: who being paſt feeling have given themſelves unto wan tonneſſe, to worke all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe with greedineſſe.</hi> Such as theſe, are ſo farre from having any right to Gods promiſes, that for the preſent they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the curſe,<note place="margin">Deut. 27. ult. Deut. 28.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8.63.</note> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently in the dint of all the plagues and thret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings in Gods booke. Wherfore let not ſuch as yet challenge any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort from the Promiſes, but let them rather la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
<pb facs="tcp:150899:27"/>to the uttermoſt of their power, in uſing all good meanes to be made capable and ſit ſubjects for mercy revealed in the Promiſes. Is it not pitty ſo many ſweet pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of life ſhould bee made, and yet thou die and be damned notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding? Pray fervently to God that he would touch thy heart with griefe for all thy ſinnes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 2.37 <hi>Luk.</hi> 15.1 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 20, 21.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> &amp; worke in thee a cleare apprehenſion of thine owne unworthineſſe, &amp; that hee would beſtow faith on thee, that by it thou mayeſt be able to go wholly out of thy ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:150899:28"/>to God, through Jeſus Chriſt for ſalvation.</p>
            <p>We having departed from him who is the God of all grace &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, are fallen into an eſtate of all baſeneſſe deſolation, and miſerie; &amp; cannot bee recovered againe into the former eſtate of ſpirituall life &amp; happineſſe, unleſſe wee be brought againe to him who is the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of life and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, even the living God: and brought to him wee can never bee, but by Faith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heh.</hi> 11.6.</note> which is nothing els but the going out of the ſoule to god through
<pb facs="tcp:150899:28"/>Chriſt, to fetch a new principall of ſpirituall life and grace, which once in <hi>Adam</hi> wee loſt, and now need.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.8, 17.</note> The which worke of faith is not wrought but by the promiſes; and being wrought in our hearts gives us a moſt ſure right and intereſt <hi>unto all the promiſes of grace.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heh.</hi> 6.12.17.</note> Thus wee through faith &amp; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience are ſaid to inherit the promiſes, therefore we are called the heires of the promiſe: the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes are as well ours, who truely beleeve, as heaven it ſelfe is. Now by theſe heavenly Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pct.</hi> 1.3.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:150899:29"/>God our Father hath engaged himſelfe as a debtour to us his poore children for all things needfull to life &amp; godlineſſe, untill that bleſſed time comes whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wee ſhall be put into full poſſeſſion of all things which wee have now on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in promiſe: at that time <hi>Faith</hi> ſhall end in fruition, and <hi>Promiſes</hi> in performance. As the ſoule is the life of the body, and faith the life of the ſoule, ſo are Gods promiſes the life of faith. For from whence hath faith his efficacie, but becauſe it layes hold
<pb facs="tcp:150899:29"/>on the free promiſes? but from whence have the promiſes their ſtrength?<note place="margin">2, <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20.</note> even from the conſtant nature of <hi>Iehovah,</hi> who alwaies gives a beeing to his word. Deſireſt thou faith? then take notice of Gods promiſes: woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt thou have thy faith like the light in the Lords Sanctuary never to go out? then acquaint thy ſelfe with Gods <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes,</hi> know them well, meditate on them, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre about them: let them bee continually in thy minde, memorie, heart and tongue. Satan laboureth in nothing
<pb facs="tcp:150899:30"/>more then to keepe us in unbeleefe, eſpecially of particular Promiſes, for he knowes if we beleeve them,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.</note> wee ſhall in all things have the victory,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph</hi> 2.</note> come before God with boldneſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. <hi>Heh.</hi> 11.</note> carry peace in our owne boſomes to our graves, and doe, and ſuffer any thing for God. Oh the abundance of ſweet cordiall comfort which all humble belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers draw by faith out of every promiſe! Now beloved,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay</hi> 66.11 12.</note> theſe precious <hi>Promiſes,</hi> (our breaſts of conſolation) whereupon our happineſſe ſo much depends, lie hid in the
<pb facs="tcp:150899:30"/>holy ſcripture, as veynes of gold in the earth. Surely, thoſe that ſearch thoſe mynes to bring to light theſe treaſures, are worthy of great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation. Wherfore I doubt not but the good paines of this bleſſed &amp; faithfull ſervant of God will finde good enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment of all the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the promiſes, that hope to entertaine them, who hath with great care and good evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of ſprituall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding diſcovered and compiled the varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and uſe of all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes in matters tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb facs="tcp:150899:31"/>ſpirituall, &amp; eternal. So that here is a medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine for every diſeaſe, &amp; a ſalve for every ſore. Read them carefully and ponder them ſeriouſly, and apply them faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And I beſeech the good Lord, who is the author of them, that by his holy ſpirit he would make them powerful, &amp; effectuall in us.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>Conſider what is ſaid, and the Lord give us underſtanding in all things.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="rules">
            <pb facs="tcp:150899:31"/>
            <head>RVLES TO BE OBSERVED IN READING THE PROMISES.</head>
            <p>WHatſoever Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe is made in generall to al the faithfull, every one muſt particularly apply it to themſelves; as <hi>Gen. 3.15.</hi> the Meſstah is promiſed to al, every one muſt apply him to themſelves.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2</hi> Whatſoever promiſe is made to any one of the
<pb facs="tcp:150899:32"/>faithfull (if there bee not ſome particular reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which tyes it to his perſon, as was to <hi>Abraham</hi> for a ſon, and his ſeed to inherit the land of Canaan) euery challd of God hath right to it: as you may ſee, Ioſuah, <hi>1.5. I will not faile thee nor forſake thee.</hi> This every one may apply to themſelves, as wee know the Holy Ghoſt applies it, <hi>Heb. 13.5. For he hath ſaid, I will never leave thee, nor forſake thee.</hi> Which teacheth us to doe the like in all the reſt of the promiſes.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> Vnder temporall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes to the Iewes, are ſet forth the excellent promiſed
<pb facs="tcp:150899:32"/>graces, which God will give to his people after the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt, <hi>Ezck. 34.25, 26, 27.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> When wee reade the conditions of the promiſes, they are not like to the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Law, made to the perfect fulfillers of them; the promiſes are Evangeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call made to thoſe which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to keepe them, and the maine conditions of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are faith.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5.</hi> In all the promiſes for increaſe of grace, or meanes of grace, or for any carthly things, wee muſt know wee ſhall have them ſo farre parformed to us, as the Lord ſeeth good for us.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb facs="tcp:150899:33"/> 
               <hi>6.</hi> In our weake endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourings to keepe the Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſes, wee muſt beleeve the performance to us, in, by, and through Chriſt; <hi>In whom all the promiſes of God are yea &amp; Amen:</hi> that is, as I conceive, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed and made good to us in him, <hi>2</hi> Cor. <hi>1.20,</hi> when wee can ſee nothing in our ſelves why they ſhould be performed to us, even then wee are to claime them for Chriſts ſake; if thou bee in Chriſt: for if thou be not in him, no promiſe belongs to thee: but that threatnings and iudgements are thy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and nothing elſe can wee claime as our due. Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row
<pb facs="tcp:150899:33"/>weeping, &amp; howling is that which God requireth of us, and not laying hand upon the comfortable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, till wee hunger after Chriſt: which God grant we may doe more and more, till wee come to be ſatiſfied with his image in the life to come. Pſal. <hi>17.15.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="promises">
            <pb facs="tcp:150899:34"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:150899:34"/>
            <div n="1" type="promise">
               <head>THE FIRST LEGACIE.</head>
               <head type="sub">Theſe promiſes I have obſerved for ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all things.</head>
               <head type="sub">Firſt about Sinne.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen wefinde nothing in our ſelves, that might move the Lord to have mercy, then apply theſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:150899:35"/>promiſes, Iſai. 43.25. <hi>I, even I am hee, that blotteth out thy tranſgreſsion for mine owne ſake, and will not remember thy ſinnes.</hi> Iſai. 44.22. <hi>I have blooted out as a thicke cloud thy tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſsions, and as a cloud thy ſinnes: returne unto mee, for I have redeemed thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ier. 31.34. <hi>I will for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give their iniquity, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member their ſin no more.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ezek. 36.25. <hi>I will ſprinkle cleane water upon you, and yee ſhall bee cleane from all your filthineſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Iſai. 57.18. <hi>I have ſeene his wayes, and will heale him, I will lead him alſo,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:150899:35"/>and reſtore comforts unto him, and to his mourners.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe promiſes are free, made by the Lord, not for any thing that is in man, as you may ſee, in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 43. from the 22 verſe, to the 25. for the Lord ſaith, They had not called upon him, but wearied the Lord, brought him no offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, yea wearied him with their ſinnes; and yet in the 25 verſe hee ſaith, for his owne ſake hee would forgive their ſinnes.</p>
               <p>Theſe promiſes wee ſhall have alwayes need of, as at our converſion,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:150899:36"/>ſo afterwards many times wee ſhall in our owne feeling finde no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in our ſelves to perſwade us of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of our ſinnes, then wee muſt flie to theſe free promiſes. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou ſeeſt nothing in thy ſelfe why the Lord ſhould pardon thy ſinnes, and therefore doubt'ſt of the pardon of them, apply, <hi>I am hee that puts away thy ſinnes for mine owne ſake.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When thy ſinnes riſe up as a cloud, that thou canſt ſee nothing but them, apply, <hi>I have put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the ſinnes as a cloud.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When thou feareſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:150899:36"/>the multitude of thy ſinnes, apply, <hi>You ſhall bee cleane from all your ſinnes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>2.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we feare, God will remember our fins before commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, to puniſh us for them, apply Ier. 31.34.</hi> I will remember his ſinne no more. <hi>Ezek. 18.22.</hi> His tranſgreſsions which he hath committed ſhall not be mentioned to him, but in the righteouſneſſe which he hath done, ſhall he live.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ezek. 33.16.</hi> None of his ſins that hee hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſhall be mentioned to him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="promise">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:150899:37"/>
               <head>The <hi>3.</hi> Promiſe.</head>
               <p>WHen thine often ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning cauſeth thee to feare that God will not pardon thee, applie, Job. 33, 27.28.29. <hi>He look eth upon men, and if any ſay I have ſinned, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted that which was right, and it profiteth mee not: hee will deliver his ſoule from going into the pit, and his life ſhall ſee the light.</hi> Loe all theſe things worketh God, oftentimes with man. Wherefore beleeve not Satan that perſwades the contrary, nor let thy corruptions make thee
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:150899:37"/>bold to preſume of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don; for though God promiſe pardon, yet it is to the penitent, not to the preſumptuous, as verſe 27.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>4.</hi> Promiſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHen thou art at the pits brinke of deſpaire, and art dryed up with ſorrow, then go to ſome faithfull Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher that is able to preach Chriſt unto thee, and apply theſe promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: Job. 33, 24, 25, 26.</hi> Then hee is gracious unto him, and ſaith, deliver him from going downe to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:150899:38"/>the pit, I have found a ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome. His fleſh ſhall bee freſher then a childes, hee ſhall returne to the dayes of his youth. Hee ſhall pray unto God, and hee ſhall bee favourable unto him, and he ſhall ſee his face with joy for hee will render unto man his righteouſneſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſai. 57.19.</hi> I create the fruit of the lips, peace, peace, to him that is farre off, &amp; to him that is neare, ſaith the Lord, and I will heale him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When thou commeſt to the uttermoſt extrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity for ſinne, apply,</hi> I will have mercy on him, and deliver him, that he
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:150899:38"/>goe not downe to the pit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When thou feareſt that God or his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters will not ſpeak peace unto thee, apply,</hi> I have received a reconciliation. I create the fruit of the lips to be peace, to them that are farre off, and to them that are neare.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When thy ſorrowes have withered thee up, apply,</hi> He ſhall returne as in the dayes of his youth, and his fleſh ſhall bee as the fleſh of a childe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If in this eſtate thou feareſt, God will not heare prayers for thee, apply,</hi> Hee ſhall pray to God, and hee will be favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:150899:39"/>to him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When thou feareſt thou ſhalt not bee able to looke upon the Lord with joy, apply,</hi> Hee ſhall ſee his face with joy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When thou ſeeſt not any thing in thy ſelfe, that ſhould cauſe thee not to believe this, apply,</hi> He will render to man his righteouſneſſe; <hi>which is (I thinke) Chriſts righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, for whoſe ſake he will doe it.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>5.</hi> Promiſe.</head>
               <p>WHen thou feeleſt ſin an heavie bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and Satan purſuing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:150899:39"/>thee with many feares, by reaſon of the ſame, flie to Chriſt, and apply, Matth. 11.28, 29. <hi>Come unto me all yee that labour and are heavie laden, and I will give you reſt.</hi> Matt. 1.21. <hi>He ſhall ſave his people from their ſinnes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Rom. 16.20. <hi>And the God of Peace ſhall bruiſe Satan under your feet ſhortly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Iſai. 32.2. <hi>And a man ſhall bee as a hiding place from the winde, and a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert frrom the tempeſt, as rivers of waters in a drie place, as the ſhadow of a great rocke in a weary land.</hi> Thus doth Chriſt to the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:150899:40"/>ſoule that flies to him.</p>
               <p>If Satan purſue thee, apply, <hi>Hee is an hiding place.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If ſtormes of tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and afflictions doe ariſe, apply, <hi>He is a refuge againſt the tempeſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If thy ſoule bee ready to faint through weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, apply, <hi>He is a river of water in a drie place,</hi> to revive thy ſpirits, and as the ſhadow of a great rocke, under which thou maiſt ſafely repoſe thy ſelfe. When thou findeſt thy ſinnes very heavy, apply, <hi>I will eaſe you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When thou haſt no reſt in thy ſoule becauſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:150899:40"/>of ſinne, apply, <hi>You ſhall finde reſt to our ſoules.</hi> He ſhall ſave his people from their ſinnes, both from the puniſhment &amp; the power.</p>
               <p>If thou feareſt length of time in temptations, apply, <hi>The God of peace ſhall bruiſe Satan under your feet ſhortly.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>6.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHen thou turneſt from ſinne, and doubteſt of the pardon of it, apply, Iſai. 1.18.</hi> Though your ſinnes bee as skarlet, they ſhall bee as white as ſnow; though
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:150899:41"/>they bee red like crimſon, they ſhall be as wooll.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſai. 55.7.</hi> Let the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked forſake his way, and the unrighteous man his thoughts, and let him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne unto the Lord, and he will have mercy on him, and to our God, for hee will abundantly pardon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Micah 7.18.19.</hi> Who is a God like unto thee, that pardoneth iniquity, and paſſeth by the tranſgreſsion of the remnant of his heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage? hee retaineth not his anger for ever, becauſe hee delighteth in mercy. Hee will turne againe, hee will have compaſsion upon us, hee will ſubdue our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:150899:41"/>and thou wilt caſt all their ſinnes into the depthes of the ſea. <hi>Prov. 28.13.</hi> He that confeſſeth and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaketh his ſinnes ſhall finde mercy. <hi>1 Iohn 1.9.</hi> If wee confeſſe our ſinnes, hee is faithfull &amp; juſt to forgive us our ſinnes, and to cleanſe us from all unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When thou ſeeſt thy ſoule of a ſinfull colour, apply,</hi> Though they be red like crimſon, they ſhall be as white as wooll.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If thou feareſt God will hardly be intreated, apply,</hi> Hee will have mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, for he is ready to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:150899:42"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>If wee feare that our ſinnes have taken ſuch ſtrong hold upon us, as wee ſhall never get from them, apply,</hi> He will clenſe us from all our unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe. <hi>See God pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth to be the clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, feare not the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the worke.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>7.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>WHen thou feeleſt many rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in thine heart and life, and would'ſt have them not onely pardoned, but ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued, apply, Hoſ. 14.5. <hi>I will heale their back-ſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</hi> Which promiſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:150899:42"/>(as I thinke) containes thus much, that God will not onely pardon, but heale us, and in ſtead of rebellious hearts and lives, will give us obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent hearts and lives; for as healing followeth the curing of ſickneſſe: ſo obedience doth the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of rebellion. Micah 7.19. <hi>Hee will ſubdue our iniquities.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When thou feeleſt ſinne very ſtrong, flie to this promiſe, and apply the ſtrength of him that promiſeth, againſt the ſtrength of ſinne: it is the Lord that hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſubdue it; what
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:150899:43"/>though Sinne and Satan joyne their force toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yet the Lord is ſtronger then all their force, wee need not doubt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>8.</hi> Promiſe.</head>
               <p>VVHen thou feeleſt thine heart hard, and full of corruption, apply, Ezek. 36.26. <hi>A new heart alſo will I give you, and a new ſpirit will I put within you, and I will take away the ſtony heart out of your fleſh, and I will give you an heart of fleſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Deut. 30.6. <hi>And the Lord thy God will circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:150899:43"/>thine heart, and the heart of thy ſeed, to love the Lord thy God with all thine heart, and with all thy ſoule, that thou maiſt live.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When thou feeleſt thine heart worldly car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, apply, <hi>I will circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe thine heart. A new heart will I give thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When nothing will breake thine heart, apply the power of Jehovah, that hath promiſed to cure thee, in taking away thy ſtonie heart.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="promise">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:150899:44"/>
               <head>The <hi>9.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>WHen thou ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt not bridle nature, but it breakes forth into vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent paſſions, to contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, apply, Iſai. 11.6. <hi>The Wolfe alſo ſhall dwell with the Lambe, and the Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pard ſhall lie downe with the Kid, and the Calfe and the young Lyon, and the fatling together, and a little child ſhall lead them.</hi> Such ſhall bee the power of the Goſpell, that thoſe which are by nature like Wolves and devouring beaſts, ſhall dwell very peaceably: and if wee finde our nature ſuch, we
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:150899:44"/>muſt apply, <hi>the Wolfe ſhall dwell with the Lambe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Micah 7.19. <hi>Hee will ſubdue our iniquities, and will caſt all our ſinnes into the depth of the ſea:</hi> that which is caſt into the Sea, as it appeareth not in ſight, ſo wee cannot get it againe, though we would: ſo will God doe by our ſinnes, caſt them out of his ſight, ſo as we ſhall not returne to them any more: preſſe him with his promiſe, and you ſhall finde more then you thinke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="promise">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:150899:45"/>
               <head>The <hi>10.</hi> Promiſe.</head>
               <p>WHen thou feeleſt thy ſelfe in bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage to ſome ſin, apply, Iohn 8.32. <hi>You ſhall know the Truth, and the Truth ſhall make you free.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Rom. 6.14. <hi>Sinne ſhall not have dominion over you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When thou feeleſt thy bondage that thou canſt not doe good, or keepe thy ſelfe from evill; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, <hi>The truth ſhall make you free.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If thy ſins often pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile againſt thee, apply, <hi>Sinne ſhall not have domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion over you.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:150899:45"/>
               <p> Pſal. 130.8. <hi>Hee ſhall redeem Iſrael from all his iniquities.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>11.</hi> Promiſe.</head>
               <p>WHen thou feeleſt ſome ſin ſo ſtrong in thee, that thou feareſt it will breake out to Gods diſhonour, and the blemiſhing of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, apply, 1 Theſſ. 5.23, 24. <hi>That your whole ſpirit, ſoule and body may be preſerved blameleſſe, unto the comming of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full is hee that calleth you, who alſo will doe it.</hi> That God which hath called
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:150899:46"/>thee, will keepe thee blameleſſe unto the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore uſe the meanes, and reſt upon the Lords faithfulneſſe, which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver faileth them which truſt in him.</p>
               <p>2. Theſſ. 3.3. <hi>But the Lord is faithfull, who ſhall ſtabliſh you and keepe you from evill.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1 Iohn 1.9. <hi>If we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe our ſinnes, he is faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and juſt to forgive us our ſinnes, and to cleanſe us from all unrighteouſneſſe.</hi> By cleanſing (as I thinke) is meant, not onely from the guilt of ſinne, but the power of it, that the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:150899:46"/>filthineſſe of it ſhall not appeare in our lives and converſations. When ſinne purſues thee hard to make thee fall, doe thou purſue the Lord with prayers, for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and doubt not of the iſſue.</p>
               <p>Micah 7.19. <hi>Hee will ſubdue our iniquities.</hi> And to theſe adde the prayer of Chriſt, John 17.15. <hi>I pray not that thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt take them out of the world, but that thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt keepe them from the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill.</hi> Now what greater evill then ſinne? there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore though thy prayers
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:150899:47"/>be but weake againſt it, yet hee hath prayed that was alway heard, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore fight and be ſure of victory.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>12.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>WHen thou art ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from ſinne by admonition, apply, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zek. 3.21. <hi>If thou warne the righteous man, that the righteous ſinne not, and he doth not ſin, hee ſhall ſurely live, becauſe he is warned.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When any admoniſh thee, obey, and it ſhall be life to thy ſoule, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore receive the admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, and apply, <hi>Hee
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:150899:47"/>ſhall live, becauſe he is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>13.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>IF thou feareſt, God will deſtroy thee for thy ſinnes, apply, Ezek. 18.30. <hi>Turne your ſelves from all your tranſgreſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſo iniquity ſhall not bee your ruine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mat. 1.21. <hi>Hee ſhall ſave his people from their ſinnes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When thou feareſt the greatneſſe or multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of thy ſinnes will be thy deſtruction, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply; <hi>Iniquity ſhall not bee your ruine.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:150899:48"/>
               <p> When thou ſeeſt no meanes of ſafety, apply, <hi>Hee</hi> (that is, Chriſt) <hi>ſhall ſave his people from their ſinnes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>14.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IF thou be tempted to uncleanneſſe, apply, Prov. 2.16.</hi> He ſhall deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thee from the ſtrange woman.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>1 Theſſ. 5.24.</hi> Thy bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die ſhall be kept blameleſſe untill the comming of Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>15.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>IF thou canſt not finde out thy ſin, for which
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:150899:48"/>God correcteth thee, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, Job. 36.9. <hi>If they bee tyed with the cords of affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, then will I ſhew them their worke, and their ſins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A wiſe father will not correct his childe, but hee will ſhew him wherefore, how elſe ſhould hee amend his fault? much more will the Lord. But wee enjoy not many promiſes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe wee ſue not for them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus farre about Sinne, the next promiſes are about Grace.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="promise">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:150899:49"/>
               <head>The <hi>16.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IN doubt of ſalvation, apply,</hi> God ſo loved the world, that he gave his only begotten Sonne, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever beleeveth in him, ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting life, <hi>Joh. 3.16.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John 5.24.</hi> Hee that heareth my word, and be leeveth on him that ſent me hath everlaſting life, and ſhall not come into condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, but is paſſed from death unto life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John 8.51.</hi> If any man keepe my ſaying, he ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſee death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John 11.25.</hi> He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeveth in me, though he
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:150899:49"/>were dead, yet ſhall hee live. And whoſoever beleeveth in me ſhall never ſee death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If thou doubt that thou ſhalt periſh, and not be ſaved, apply,</hi> Hee that beleeves in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſhall not periſh, but ſhall have ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life, and ſhall not come into condemnation. <hi>Labour to beleeve theſe Promiſes, and that is all that is required of thee, for the obtaining of what is promiſed.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>17.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>WHen thou findeſt thine heart as a wilderneſſe barren of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:150899:50"/>good, apply, Eſa. 35.1, 2. <hi>The wilderneſſe and the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litarie place ſhall bee glad for them: and the deſart ſhall rejoyce, and bloſſome as the Roſe. It ſhall bloſſome abundantly, and rejoyce e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with joy and ſinging.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This promiſe is made to the Church, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry member of it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie it to themſelves: therfore when thou fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt thine heart as a de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſart wildernes and waſte ground, void of good, full of bryers &amp; thornes of ſinne, then know, thou ſhalt not onely bring forth ſweet ſmelling graces, like roſes, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:150899:50"/>all abundance of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p>Pro. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.28. <hi>The righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſhal flouriſh as a branch.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Prov. 13 4 <hi>The ſoule of the diligent ſhall be made fat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hoſ. 14.5, 6. <hi>I will be as the dew to Iſrael, hee ſhall grow as the Lilly, and caſt forth his roots like Leba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non. His branches ſhall ſpread, and his beauty be as the Olive tree, and his ſmell as Lebanon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When we want meanes to make us fruitfull, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, <hi>The Lord will be a dew to Iſrael.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When wee deſire to flouriſh and grow up in grace, apply, <hi>He ſhall grow
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:150899:51"/>as the Lilly, his branches ſhall ſpread.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If thou wouldeſt ſhine forth in the beauty of holines, apply, <hi>His beauty ſhal be as the Olive-tree &amp; as the Lilies,</hi> whoſe glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie is greater then <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> in all his royalty.</p>
               <p>If thou wouldeſt have thy graces ſend ſorth a ſweet ſmell, apply, <hi>His ſmell ſhall be as Lebanon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If thou feareſt the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of this eſtate, apply, <hi>Hee ſhall faſten his rootes, as the trees of Leba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It matters not how great our barrennes bee, when God will be a dew
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:150899:51"/>to us: it will quickly make us fruitful, we ſhall bring forth fruits glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the ſight, as the Lilly, and as the Olive tree, and the ſent of our graces ſhall bee a ſweet ſmelling ſavour, as the trees of Lebanon. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore though thou feeleſt thy heart yet barren, and thou haſt uſed meanes long, and yet art not fruitfull, ſtill uſe the meanes, and beleeve, for therein did <hi>Abraham</hi> glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God that hee belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved above hope, that <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah</hi> ſhould have a ſonne, whoſe wombe was bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, and by yeares paſt
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:150899:52"/>child bearing: ſo though thine heart remaine bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren in thine owne fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, after long uſe of meanes, yet ſtill follow ſeeing in the meanes, and beleeve, for wee have as ſure promiſes, and as faithfull a perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, as <hi>Abraham</hi> had, Jeſus Chriſt, yeſterday, and to day, and the ſame for ever.</p>
               <p>John 7.38. <hi>He that be leeveth on mee, out of his belly ſhall flow rivers of water of life.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="promise">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:150899:52"/>
               <head>The <hi>18.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>WHe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou art trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for want of holineſſe, apply, Exod. 19.6. <hi>You ſhall bee an holy nation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Deut.28.9. <hi>And the Lord ſhall eſtabliſh thee an holy people unto himſelfe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Lord will make thee holy, therefore Sin, nor Satan, nor wicked men cannot hinder thy holineſſe: for hee that makes thee holy is ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then all, and doth what he will.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Theſſ. 5.23.24. <hi>The God of peace ſhall ſanctifie you throughout, in ſpirit,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:150899:53"/>ſoule, and body. Faithfull is hee which calleth you, which will alſo doe it.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>19.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>WHen thou canſt not offer up any ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to God of prayer or praiſe, or thy ſelfe in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, apply, Exod. 19.6. <hi>Yee ſhall be unto mee a kingdome of prieſts.</hi> God promiſeth that wee ſhall be prieſts, that is, ſuch as ſhall offer up ſacrifice unto him, for that was the prieſts office. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when thou findeſt thy ſelfe unable to pray, or praiſe the Lord, or to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:150899:53"/>offer up thy ſelfe to God, ſoule and body, ſtrive in faith grounded on the promiſes, that hee which commanded, hath alſo promiſed to make us a-able to do it, for he hath ſaid, <hi>Wee ſhall bee Prieſts,</hi> Malac. 1.11. <hi>In every place incenſe ſhall bee offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to my name, and a pure offering;</hi> which is ſpoken of the beleeving Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, therefore thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one of them, ſhalt be able to offer up pure of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="promise">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:150899:54"/>
               <head>The <hi>20.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>WHen thou feeleſt littlegrace, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, faith, love, repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, all very little, apply, Job. 8.7. <hi>Though thy beginning be ſmall, yet thy latter end ſhall greatly increaſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Matth. 13.12. <hi>Whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hath, to him ſhall be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and hee ſhall have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore let not thy ſmall beginnings diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage thee; but if thou canſt prove thou haſt ſome grace, then joyne faith and diligence toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:150899:54"/>&amp; they will quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make thee rich.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>21.</hi> Promiſe.</head>
               <p>WHen thou findeſt al thy graces very weake, &amp; no ſtrength to performe any ſpirituall duty, either prayer or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, or any other duty, then apply, Pſalme 29.11. <hi>The Lord will give ſtrength unto his people.</hi> Iſa. 40.29.31. <hi>Hee giveth power to the faint, and to them which have no might he increaſeth ſtrength. They that wait upon the Lord ſhall renew their ſtrength,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:150899:55"/>they ſhall mount up with wings as Eagles, they ſhall run and not be weary, they ſhall walke and not faint.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When thou feeleſt thy ſelfe faint, ſtay thy ſelfe with this promiſe, <hi>Hee giveth ſtrength to him that fainteth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When thou feeleſt no power, apply, <hi>to him that hath no ſtrength he increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth power.</hi> If thou haſt loſt thy power, then ſtay thy ſelfe with this, <hi>they ſhall renew their ſtrength.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If thou art ready to give over through wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſſe, then gather ſtrength from this, <hi>They ſhall run and not be weary,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:150899:55"/>and walke and not be faint.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if thou findeſt not theſe promiſes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed unto thee, either thou endeavoreſt not to keepe the conditions, or elſe thou art negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in ſearching out the promiſes, or cold in ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for them: the Lord will be ſought to for the performance.</p>
               <p>Iſai. 41.10. <hi>I am thy God, I will ſtrengthen thee, yea I will helpe thee, yea I will uphold thee with the right hand of my righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe.</hi> Iſa. 26.4. <hi>Truſt thou in the Lord for ever, for in the Lord</hi> Jehovah <hi>is everlaſting ſtrength.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:150899:56"/>
               <p> To know there is ſtrength in the Lord is no comfort, unleſſe wee know it ſhall bee for us. Therefore ſince it is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for a comfort, it muſt include this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, <hi>Thus the Lords ſtrength for evermore ſhall be imployed for our good.</hi> Therfore when we want for either ſoule or body, wee muſt fixe our confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in him, who will-not faile us, if wee ſeeké unto him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="promise">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:150899:56"/>
               <head>The <hi>22.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHen thou feeleſt thine heart dryed up for want of grace, that thou canſt not ſend forth any water of grace in thy thoughts, words, and workes, apply, Iſai. 44.3.</hi> I will poure water up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him that is thirſty, and floods upon the dry ground.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſai. 58.11.</hi> The Lord ſhall ſatisfie thy ſoule in drought, and make fat thy bones, and thou ſhalt be like a watred garden, and like a ſpring of waters, whoſe waters faile not.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ier. 17.8.</hi> Hee ſhall bee as a tree planted by the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:150899:57"/>that ſpreadeth out her roots by the river, and ſhall not ſee when heate com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth: but her leafe ſhall be greene, and ſhall not be carefull in the yeare of drought, neither ſhall ceaſe from yeelding fruit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jer. 31.12.</hi> Their ſoule ſhall bee as a watred gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jam. 4.6.</hi> God giveth grace unto the humble.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſa. 35.6, 7.</hi> In the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe ſhall waters breake out, and ſtreames in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert. And the parched ground ſhall become a poole, and the thirſty land ſprings of waters. <hi>That is, the moſt barren heart
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:150899:57"/>ſhall abound with grace, according to that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe John 7.</hi> Out of their bellies ſhall flow rivers of the waters of Life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſa. 41.17.18.19.</hi> When the poore and needie ſeeke water, and there is none, and their tongues faile for thirſt, I the Lord will heare them, I the God of Iſrael will not forſake them: I will open rivers in high places; and fountaines in the middeſt of the valleys: I will make the wilderneſſe a poole of water, and the drie land ſprings of water. I will plant in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the Cedar, the Shittah tree, and the Mirtle, and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:150899:58"/>the Oyle tree: I will ſet in the deſert the Firre tree, and the Pine, and the Boxe tree together. <hi>So now though thou feeleſt thy heart barren, know that God will bee thy Gardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to thy barren heart, to make pooles, &amp; plant pleaſant grapes of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; therefore ſeeing hee taketh upon himſelfe the worke, feare not the bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the ground, for hee will make it good as a fruitfull garden.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="promise">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:150899:58"/>
               <head>The <hi>23.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IF thou feeleſt thou wanteſt the Spirit of God, apply, Ezek. 36.27.</hi> I will put my Spirit within you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luke 11.13.</hi> If yee then being evill, know how to give good gifts unto your children: how much more ſhall your heavenly Father give the holy Spirit to them that aske him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Joel 2.28.29.</hi> I will poure out my Spirit upon all fleſh, and your ſonnes and your daughters ſhall prophecie, your old men ſhall dreame dreames, and your young men ſhall ſee viſions.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:150899:59"/>And alſo upon the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and upon the hand maids in thoſe dayes will I poure out my Spirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Joh. 6.14.16.17.18.</hi> And I will pray the Father, and hee ſhall give you another Comforter, that hee may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide with you for ever: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the Spirit of truth, hee dwelleth in you, and ſhall be in you, I will not leave you comfortleſſe, I will come to you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When thou canſt not pray thy ſelfe, ſtay thy ſelfe on theſe prayers that Chriſt hath prayed, to the Father to give the Spirit, &amp; he was heard in all hee prayed for, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:150899:59"/>thou mayſt claime it, though thy prayers be but weake.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>24.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>WHen thou lookeſt upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the great love of God unto thee, and canſt not finde thine heart inlarged in loving God againe, apply this promiſe, Deut, 30.9. <hi>I will circumciſe thine heart, that thou maiſt love the Lord thy God with all thine heart, and with all thy ſoule.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="promise">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:150899:60"/>
               <head>The <hi>25.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>WHe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou canſt not bring thine heart to delight in the Lord, apply, Iſai. 41.16. <hi>Thou ſhalt rejoyce in the Lord, &amp; glory in the holy One of Iſrael.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Pſalm. 89.16. <hi>In thy name ſhall they rejoyce all the day: and in thy righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes ſhall they be exalted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Job. 22.26. <hi>For then ſhalt thou have thy delight in the Almighty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Pſalm. 33.21. <hi>For our heart ſhall rejoyce in him: becauſe wee have truſted in his holy name.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When thou ſeeſt cauſe
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:150899:60"/>of rejoycing in the Lord, and yet canſt not move thine affections, apply, <hi>They ſhall rejoyce in him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If through many trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and temptations, thou findeſt thy joyes often interrupted, apply, <hi>they ſhall rejoice continually in thy name.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>26.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>WHen we ſeele not the feare of God in our hearts, apply, Jer. 32.40. <hi>I will put my feare in their hearts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If wee would have a reverent feare of God, when wee performe any
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:150899:61"/>holy duty, or at other times, as thou feeleſt thy need, ſo urge the Lord with this his promiſe, for he delights to be ſued to, upon his promiſe, by his ſervants, Ezek. 36.37. <hi>I will yet for this be enquired of by the houſe of Iſrael to doe it for them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>27</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>WHe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou canſt not bring thine heart to praiſe the Lord, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, Iſai. 43.21. <hi>This people have I formed for my ſelfe, they ſhall ſhew forth my praiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Joel 2.26. <hi>Yee ſhall eat
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:150899:61"/>in plenty, and be ſatisfied, and praiſe the name of the Lord your God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Pſal. 22.29. <hi>They ſhall praiſe the Lord that ſeeke him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When thou ſeeſt what great things God hath done for thee, and findeſt not thy ſelfe able to ſet forth his praiſe, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, <hi>They ſhall ſet forth my praiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When thou findeſt thy ingratefull heart not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the mercies thou enjoyeſt, ſo as they ſtir thee not up to praiſe the Lord, apply, <hi>He ſhall eate and bee ſatisfied, and praiſe the name of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="promise">
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:150899:62"/>
               <head>The <hi>28.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>WHen thou ſeeſt thy want of wiſedome makes thee not walke like a Chriſtian, ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blameably as thou ought apply, Jam. 1.5. <hi>If any of you lacke wiſedome, let him aske of God, that giveth to all men liberally, and up braideth not, and it ſhall be given him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When thou findeſt thou want'ſt wiſedome to improve thine affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to the beſt advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, or for the ordering of thy actions, occaſions and courſe of life, to Gods glory &amp; the good
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:150899:62"/>of others, and thy ſelfe, then faile not to aske wiſdome, and doubt not of the obtaining of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>29.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>WHen thou canſt not underſtand the voice of God in his word, or workes, not knowing what to learne by them, apply, Iſa. 35.5. <hi>The eares of the deafe ſhall bee unſtopped.</hi> That is, thoſe that were as deafe not underſtanding any thing, ſhall be made to heare, that is, to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand.</p>
               <p>John 10.16. <hi>Other
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:150899:63"/>ſheepe I have, which are not of this fold, them alſo I muſt bring, and they ſhall heare my voice.</hi> Which is a promiſe to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, that they ſhall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the voice of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>30.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>IF thou canſt not ſee into the divine myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Goſpell, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, Iſai. 35.5. <hi>The eyes of the blinde ſhall be opened.</hi> Iſai. 42.7. <hi>Hee ſhall open the eyes of the blinde.</hi> Luk. 4.18. <hi>Hee hath ſent mee to recover ſight to the blinde.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe places are what
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:150899:63"/>Chriſt will doe to his people, therefore wee need not feare our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, ſeeing Chriſt is our Phyſitian. If every creature doth that, for which it was ordained, then hee will ſurely doe that which hee was ſent to doe of the Father, to give ſight to the blinde.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>31.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>WHen thou ſeeſt a good way, &amp; haſt no power to walke in it, or art to performe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny duty, ordinary or extraordinary, and feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt no ſtrength to walke
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:150899:64"/>in that way, apply, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zek. 36.27. <hi>And I will put my Spirit within you, and cauſe you to walke in my ſtatutes, and yee ſhall keepe my judgements, and doe them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When thou lookeſt at the greatneſſe of the duty which God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, looke alſo at the largeneſſe of his promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes for the keeping of them, and then thou wilt not be diſcouraged at it. What matters it what he commands, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wee haue his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe?</p>
               <p>If thou feareſt the ſtrictneſſe of thy wayes
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:150899:64"/>that thou ſhalt not bee able to walke in them, though thou ſtep into them ſometimes, ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then thy faith in this promiſe, I will give thee my Spirit to cauſe thee to walke in my wayes. Can ſinne or Satan then reſiſt? Nay ſurely the Spirit is ſtronger, and greater is hee that is in us, then thoſe that are againſt us. And when wee ſee great duties which God commands, and feare wee ſhall want ſtrength to doe them, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, Hee hath ſaid, <hi>You ſhall keepe my judgements, and doe them.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:150899:65"/>
               <p> Iſai. 40.31. <hi>They ſhall runne, and not bee weary; they ſhall walke, and not bee faint.</hi> That is, Thoſe which of themſelves could not ſtep one ſtep, ſhall bee able to runne ſwiftly in the wayes of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>32.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHen thou wanteſt memory to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the word of God, apply, John 14.26.</hi> But the Comforter which is the Holy Ghoſt, whom the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will ſend in my name, hee ſhall teach you all things, and bring all things
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:150899:65"/>to your reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever I have ſaid unto you,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>33.</hi> Legacie</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHen thou ſeeſt thine ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; feareſt thou ſhalt not bee able to glorifie God as thou mighteſt, if thou had'ſt more knowledge, ſtirre up thy ſelfe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, and apply, Jer. 31.33.34.</hi> Thus ſaith the Lord, I will put my Law in their inward parts, and write it in their hearts, and they ſhall all know mee, ſaith the Lord, from the greateſt to the leaſt. <hi>Hoſea 2.20.</hi> Thou ſhalt know
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:150899:66"/>the Lord, <hi>Prov. 1.23.</hi> I will poure out my Spirit un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, I will make knowne my words unto you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pſal. 25.9.12.14.</hi> The meeke will he guide in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and the meeke will hee teach his way. What man is hee that feareth the Lord? him ſhall he teach in the way that hee ſhall chuſe. The ſecret of the Lord is with them that feare him: and hee will ſhew them his cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prov. 2.4.9.11.12.13.</hi> If thou ſeckeſt her as ſilver and ſearcheſt for her as for treaſures. Then ſhalt thou underſtand righteouſneſſe,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:150899:66"/>and judgement, and equity, yea every good path. Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion ſhall preſerve thee, underſtanding ſhall keope thee, to deliver thee from the way of the evill man, from the man that ſpeaketh froward things: who leave the paths of uprightneſſe, to walke in the wayes of darkeneſſe. <hi>Iſai. 11.9.</hi> The earth ſhall bee full of the knowledge of the Lord. <hi>Prov. 8.17.</hi> Thoſe that ſeeke me earely, ſhall finde mee. <hi>Iſai. 35.8.</hi> The foole ſhall not erre. <hi>John. 7.17.</hi> if any man will doe his will, he ſhall know of the doctrine whether it bee of God, or whether I ſpeake of my ſelfe.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:150899:67"/>
                  <hi>Iſai. 32.3, 4.</hi> The eyes of them that ſee ſhall not bee dimme, and the eares of them that heare ſhall har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. The heart alſo of the raſh ſhall underſtand know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When thou thinkeſt of the great myſtery of God manifeſt in the fleſh, and of one divine eſſence, and three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, &amp; ſeeſt thine owne inability to conceive of this great God, apply,</hi> They ſhall all know the Lord: The heart of the foole ſhall underſtand.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When wee feare God will not reveale his will to us; apply,</hi> I will poure
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:150899:67"/>out my minde to you. Hee will teach the humble his wayes. he will teach him the way he ſhall chuſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If thou feareſt that though God reveale his will, yet thy ignorance is ſuch, as thou ſhalt not be able to underſtand it, apply,</hi> I will cauſe you to underſtand. Thou ſhalt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand judgement, righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, equity, and every good path.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If thou feareſt men will draw thee away to errour, apply,</hi> Counſell ſhall preſerve thee, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding ſhall keepe thee and deliver thee from the evill way, and from the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:150899:68"/>man that ſpeaketh froward things, and from them that leave the wayes of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, to walke in the wayes of darkeneſſe. The fooles ſhall not erre. He ſhall know the doctrine whether it be of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>34.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>IF thou deſireſt Grace, and thy deſires are not ſatisfied, apply, pſalm. 34.7. <hi>Delight thy ſelfe alſo in the Lord, and hee ſhall give thee the deſires of thine heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Pſal. 145.19. <hi>Hee will fulfill the deſires of them that feare him.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:150899:68"/>
               <p> Pſal. 81.10. <hi>Open thy mouth wide, and I will fill it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Matth. 5, 6. <hi>Bleſſed are they which doe hunger and thirſt after righteouſneſſe, for they ſhall be filled.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Prov. 10.24, <hi>The deſire of the righteous ſhall bee granted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Doeſt thou deſire grace? feareſt thou God will not grant thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires? apply, <hi>Hee ſhall give thee thy hearts deſire: Hee will fulfill thy deſire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Feareſt thou that if he give grace, it will bee but a little? apply, <hi>Open thy mouth wide, and I will fill it. Thou ſhalt be filled.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:150899:69"/>
               <p> Iſai. 30.18. <hi>Bleſſed are all they which wait for him. Hee will certainely have mercy upon thee at the voyce of thy crie, when he heareth hee will anſwer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When thou beginneſt to faint with waiting, apply, <hi>Hee will certainely have mercie upon thee.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>35.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>VVHen thou feeleſt thine hart dead, that it will not ſtirre to God or goodneſſe, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, Pſ. 22.26. <hi>Your heart ſhall live for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Prov. 3.21.22. <hi>Keepe ſound wiſdome and diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:150899:69"/>ſo ſhall they be life un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy ſoule.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Iſai. 57.15. <hi>I dwell in the high and holy place, with him alſo that is of a contrite and humble ſpirit, to revive the ſpirit of the humble, and to revive the heart of contrite ones.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Amos. 5.4. <hi>Seeke the Lord and yee ſhall live.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When thou feareſt thou ſhalt never over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the deadneſſe of thine heart, apply, <hi>Your heart ſhall live. Seeke the Lord, and yee ſhall live.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When thou haſt got ſome life, and feareſt the loſing of it, apply, <hi>Your hearts ſhall live for ever.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="promise">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:150899:70"/>
               <head>The <hi>36.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>WHen thou feareſt thou ſhalt fall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and beginneſt to decline, apply, 1. Cor. 1.8. <hi>Chriſt ſhall alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme you unto the end, that yee may be blameleſſe in the day of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Pſal. 16.8. <hi>I have ſet the Lord alwayes before me: becauſe hee is at my right hand I ſhall not bee moved.</hi> Pſalm, 145.14. <hi>The Lord upholdeth all that fall: and raiſeth up all thoſe that bee bowed downe.</hi> Pſalm. 92.12.14. <hi>The righteous ſhall flouriſh like the Palme-tree. He ſhall
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:150899:70"/>grow like a Cedar in Leba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non. They ſhall ſtill bring forth fruit in old age: they ſhall be fat and flouriſhing.</hi> Pſal. 1.3. <hi>And he ſhall be like a tree: planted by the rivers of water, that bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth his fruit in his ſeaſon: his leafe alſo ſhall not wither,</hi> Pſal. 31.24. <hi>Hee ſhall ſtabliſh thine heart.</hi> Job. 11.15.27. <hi>Thou ſhalt bee ſtedfaſt, thine age ſhall bee clearer then the noone day, thou ſhalt ſhine forth, thou ſhalt be as the morning.</hi> Judg. 5.31. <hi>They that love the Lord ſhall bee as the Sunne, when it goeth forth in his might.</hi> Now we ſee that nothing can
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:150899:71"/>hinder the Sunne in his might, but it chaſeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the darkeneſſe and clouds before it, and ceaſeth not till it hath runne his race: ſo ſhall the childe of God, for the Lord hath ſaid it; wee need not doubt of it. If thou feareſt thine owne weakneſſe, and the power of temptation, with the ſubtilty of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, apply, That God whoſe power and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome over-reacheth all other, hath ſaid, <hi>Hee will confirme you to the end. He ſhall ſtabliſh thine heart, thy leafe ſhall not fade.</hi> Art thou hard purſued
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:150899:71"/>by ſinne and Satan, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, that God whoſe power and wiſedome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-reacheth all, he hath ſaid, <hi>He will ſtabliſh thee.</hi> If thou bee ready to fall and faint, apply, <hi>The Lord upholdeth all them that fall, and lifteth up all them that are ready to fall: thou ſhalt pot ſlide.</hi> It thou fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt that though thou be kept fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſin, yet thy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſhall decay, apply, <hi>The righteous ſhall flouriſh as a Palme-tree, and ſhall grow as a Cedar in Leba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non. They ſhall bring forth fruit in their age, they ſhall be fat and flouriſhing: thou ſhalt bring forth fruit in
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:150899:72"/>ſeaſon: thou ſhalt be ſtable; thine age ſhall appeare more cleare then noone day. Thou ſhalt ſhine as the morning.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>37.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>WHen wee are falne and ſeare the Lord will leave us ſo, then ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, Pſal. 55.22. <hi>Caſt thy burden upon the Lord, and hee ſhall ſuſtaine thee: hee ſhall never ſuffer the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous to be moved.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Pſal. 37.24.28. <hi>Though he fall, hee ſhall not bee ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly caſt downe, for the Lord upholdeth him with
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:150899:72"/>his hand. For the Lord lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth judgement, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaketh not his Saints, they are preſerved for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Jer. 32.40. <hi>I will put my feare in their hearts, that they ſhall not depart from mee.</hi> When thou art fallen, and felleſt a great loade of ſinne or miſery upon thee, and no power to unload thy ſelfe, thy graces ſo weak, that they will not helpe thee, and therefore thou thinkeſt thy ſtate deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, apply, <hi>Though he fall, he ſhall not bee caſt off, for the Lord putteth under his hand.</hi> Therefore though ſinne and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:150899:73"/>bee never ſo heavy to preſſe thee downe, yet that powerfull hand of God, when thou art at the loweſt, being under thee, ſhall eaſily lift thee up, thou haſt his promiſe <hi>he will not ſuffer thee to fall for ever.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>38.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord hath for ſaken thee in thine owne feeling, and thou ſeareſt hee will not returne againe, apply, Iſai. 54, 7, 8, 9, 10.</hi> For a ſmall moment have I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken thee: but with great mercies will I gather thee.
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:150899:73"/>In a little wrath I had my face from thee for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but with everlaſting kindneſſe will I have mercy on thee, ſaith thee Lord thy Redeemer. For this is as the waters of Noah unto mee; for as I have ſworne that the Waters of Noah ſhall no more goe over the earth: ſo have I ſworne that I would not bee wroth with thee, nor rebuke thee. For the mountaines ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, and the hils ſhall bee removed: but my kindneſſe ſhall not depart from thee; neither ſhall the covenant of my peace bee removed, ſaith the Lord that hath mercie on thee.</p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:150899:74"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Gen. 17.7.</hi> I will eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh my covenant betwixt thee and me, and everlaſting covenant to bee a God unto thee.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Deut. 31.8.</hi> I will bee with thee, I will not faile thee, neither forſake thee, feare not, neither bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>1 King. 6.13.</hi> I will not for ſake my people.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>2 Chron. 15.2.</hi> The Lord is with you while you be with him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Job. 8.20.</hi> Behold, God will not caſt away a perfect man.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Job. 36.5.</hi> Behold, God is mighty, and deſpiſeth not any</p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:150899:74"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Hoſea 2.19.20.</hi> I will betroth thee unto mee for ever; yea I will betroth thee unto mee in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and in judgement, and in loving kindneſſe, and in mercies. I will even be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troth thee unto me in faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>39.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>WHen thou feeleſt thy vileneſſe, and feareſt the Lord will loath thee for it, apply, Levit. 26.11. <hi>My soule ſhall not abhorre you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hoſea 14.4. <hi>I will love them freely, for mine an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:150899:75"/>is turned away from them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Deut. 7.13. <hi>I will love thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>John 14.21.23. <hi>Hee that loveth mee ſhall be lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of my Father, and I will love him, and will ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt my ſelfe to him, my Father will love him, and wee will come unto him, and make our abode with him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Jer. 3.41. <hi>I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce over them to doe them good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When thou ſeeſt a multitude of ſinnes, ſo that thou ſeemeſt moſt loathſome, apply, <hi>My ſoule ſhall not loath you.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:150899:75"/>
               <p> When thou ſeeſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in thy ſelfe that ſhould move him to love thee, but all to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, apply, <hi>I will love them freely.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If thou feareſt thy many ſinnes will cauſe the Lord not to delight in thee, apply, <hi>I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If thou feareſt thy ſin will cauſe the Lord to hide himſelfe from thee, apply, <hi>I will ſhew mine owne ſelfe unto him.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>40.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>WHen thou feeleſt thy ſpirituall po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:150899:76"/>apply, Math. 5.3. <hi>Bleſſed are the poore in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; for theirs is the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Iſai. 66.2. <hi>To him will I looke, ſaith the Lord, that is poore and of a contrite ſpirit, and trembleth at my words.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When thou feeleſt thy ſinnes many, and thy graces very little, and therefore feareſt that ſuch a miſerable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as them art, ſhall not inherit heaven, apply, <hi>Bleſſed are the poore in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, for theirs is the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If thou feareſt the Lord will not looke upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:150899:76"/>thee, apply <hi>To him will I looke, ſaith the Lord, that is of a contrite ſpirit.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>41.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHen thou art in a ſtrait, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt not what to chuſe, either in ſome truth, or in ſomething that is to bee done, that thou knoweſt not what to chuſe, apply, Pſalm, 25.22.</hi> Him ſhall hee teach in the way that he ſhall chuſe, <hi>verſe 13.</hi> His ſoule ſhall dwell at eaſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prov. 3.6.</hi> In all thy wayes acknowledge him,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:150899:77"/>and hee ſhall direct thy pathes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prov. 16.3.</hi> Commit thy workes unto the Lord, and thy thoughts ſhall bee eſtabliſhed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſai. 30.21.</hi> And thine eare ſhall heare a word be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde thee, ſaying, This is the way, walke yee in it, when yee turne to the right hand, and when yee turne to the left.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſai. 58.11.</hi> The Lord ſhall guide thee continually.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſai. 61.8.</hi> I will direct their worke in truth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jer. 31.9.</hi> I will cauſe them to walke by the rivers of waters, in a ſtraight way wherein they ſhall not ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:150899:77"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>When thou doubt'ſt of ſome truth, apply,</hi> Hee ſhall teach him the way that he ſhall chuſe, his ſoule ſhall dwell at eaſe. Thine eares ſhall heare a voice behinde thee, ſaying, this is the way walke in it. I will direct thy way in truth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When thou art think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what courſe to take, and feareſt thou ſhalt not know what the Lord would have thee to do, apply,</hi> Thy thoughts ſhall be directed, hee ſhall direct thy wayes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When thou feareſt thy weakeneſſe will at ſometimes carry thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray, apply,</hi> The Lord will
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:150899:78"/>guide thee continually. The Lord will lead thee in a ſtrait way, that thou ſhalt not ſtumble.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>42.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>WHen thou feareſt that Satan by his power and ſubtiltie will cauſe thee to fall, and art troubled with his temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, apply, Gen. 3.15. <hi>Hee ſhall bruiſe his head.</hi> Therefore feare not, for Chriſt hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrowne all his power and ſubtilty, that hee cannot do us any harme. Pſal. 19.3.4. <hi>Surely hee
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:150899:78"/>ſhall deliver thee from the ſnare of the fowler. He ſhall cover thee with his fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: and under his wings ſhalt thou truſt: his truth ſhall thy ſhield and buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Rom. 16.20. <hi>The God of peace ſhall bruiſe Satan under your feet ſhortly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Doth Sathan preſſe thee with ſtrong tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptations, &amp; feareſt thou his power, apply, <hi>He ſhall bruiſe his head. Hee will cover thee under his wings, and thou ſhalt be ſafe under his feathers, his ſtrength ſhall be thy buckler.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Feareſt thou his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty? apply, <hi>Hee ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:150899:79"/>thee from thee ſnare of the fowler, and bruiſe his head,</hi> wherein lyes all his power and plots.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>43.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>WHe thou canſt mot profit by the Word of God, or his workes of mercy, or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, apply, Iſai. 48.17. <hi>I am the Lord thy God which teacheth thee to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, which leadeth thee by the way that thou ſhouldeſt goe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mat. 21.41. <hi>The King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God ſhall bee taken from you, and given to a
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:150899:79"/>Nation bringing forth the fruites thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is a promiſe, that the Gentiles ſhall bring forth the fruits of the Goſpell, therefore every beleeving Gentile may apply it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>44.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>WHen thou findeſt thy ſelfe not like the people of God, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in heart or life, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, Jer. 32.39. <hi>I will give them one heart, and one way.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When thou ſeeſt thine heart not like the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:150899:80"/>of God, either in their affection of God, or his people, or ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, or in their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing for ſinne, apply, <hi>I will give them one heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When thou ſeeſt thy life and converſation not ſo holy as the people of God, apply, <hi>I will give them one way.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>45.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IF thou wouldeſt have the bleſſing of the Lord to reſt upon thee, apply, Pſalme 5.12.</hi> The Lord will bleſſe the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</p>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:150899:80"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Deut. 7.13.</hi> I will bleſſe thee.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pſalm. 3.8.</hi> Thy bleſsing is upon thy people.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pſal. 24.5.</hi> Hee ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the bleſsing from the Lord, and righteouſneſſe from the God of his ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pſal. 115.12.13.</hi> The Lord will bleſſe us, hee will bleſſe the houſe of Iſrael, he will bleſſe the houſe of Aaron. Hee will bleſſe them that feare the Lord, both ſmall and great.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="promise">
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:150899:81"/>
               <head>The <hi>46.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>IF thou wouldeſt bee a bleſſing in thy place, apply, Gen. 12.2. <hi>I will bleſſe thee, and thou ſhalt be a bleſsing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ezek. 34.26. <hi>I will make them about my hill a bleſsing.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>47.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVHe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt thy ſelfe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the wicked in their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt worſhip and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, apply. 2 Cor. 6.16, 17, 18.</hi> I will dwell in them, and walke in them,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:150899:81"/>and I will be their God, and they ſhall bee my people, Wherefore come out from among them, and be yee ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate, ſaith the Lord; and touch not the uncleane thing, and I will receive you; and will be a father unto you, and yee ſhall bee my ſonnes and daughters, ſaith the Lord Almighty.</p>
               <p>Thus farre of Grace; the next Promiſes are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the meanes of Grace, either ordinarie, or extraordinarie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="promise">
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:150899:82"/>
               <head>The <hi>48.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>IN every Ordinance thou maiſt apply this promiſe, Iſai. 12.3. <hi>With joy ſhall you draw water out of the Wels of ſalvation.</hi> Now in that it is ſaid, out of the Wels of ſalvation, and not Well, I thinke we ought to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it to every ordinance of God, ſo as wee are to uſe them with a comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table perſwaſion, that wee ſhall receive abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of grace from them. As the Lord pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth wee ſhall draw waters from out of them, wee ſhall not onely uſe
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:150899:82"/>them but draw from them with joy. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when we pray, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate, heare, conferre, faſt, in every duty, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply this promiſe, and you ſhall finde him faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full which promiſeth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>49.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHen thou pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt apply theſe promiſes for the ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thening of thy faith, and for thy hearing. Mat. 7.7.</hi> Aske, and it ſhall bee given you, ſeeke and you ſhall find, knocke and it ſhall bee ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned unto you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.6. Pray to the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:150899:83"/>Father which ſeeth in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, and thy Father which ſeeth in ſecret ſhall reward thee openly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.22. And all things whatſoever ye ſhall aske in prayer, beleeving yee ſhall receive it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John</hi> 14.13.14. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever yee ſhall aske in my name, I will doe it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John</hi> 16.24. Aske and yee ſhall receive, that your joy may be full.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John</hi> 15.7. Aske what you will, and it ſhall be done unto you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſai.</hi> 65.24. Before they call I will anſwere, and whiles they are yet ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, I will heare.</p>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:150899:83"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Job.</hi> 22.7. Thou ſhalt make thy prayers unto him, and he ſhall heare thee, and if thou ſeeke him he will be found.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>50.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>WHen thou medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, apply theſe promiſes, Prov. 14.22. <hi>Mercy and truth ſhall bee to them that deviſe good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Pſalm. 103.17.18. <hi>The loving kindneſſe of the Lord endureth for ever, to them which thinke upon his commandements to doe them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Phil. 4.8, 9. <hi>Thinke on theſe things, which ye have
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:150899:84"/>both learned, and received, and heard, and ſeene in mee, and the God of peace ſhall be with you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If thou deſireſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, or the truth of God to bee for thy good, or the loving kindneſſe of the Lord to bee for ever towards thee, and that God which brings peace with him, to bee with thee, then meditate on good things, and with ſuch a meditation, as may ſtirre thee up to practiſe, and then all theſe promiſes ſhall ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be performed to thee. And becauſe meditation is an hard duety, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:150899:84"/>encourage thy ſelfe to it by the benefit it brings, &amp; it being a way of God, hee will give thee his Spirit to cauſe thee to walke in it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>51.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IN meditating confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and reading of the word of God, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, Joſhua 1.8.</hi> Let not this booke of the Law de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of thy mouth, but meditate therein day and night, that thou mayſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to doe according to all that is written therein: for then thou ſhalt make thy way proſperous, and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:150899:85"/>then thou ſhalt have good ſucceſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>52.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IN reading of the Word, if wee under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not, apply theſe promiſes, Prov.</hi> 1.23. In will poure out my Spirit unto you. I will make known my words unto you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.4. It gives ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty to the ſimple: to the young men knowledge and diſcretion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 19.8. The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of the Lord is pure, inlightning the eyes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="promise">
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:150899:85"/>
               <head>The <hi>53.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>VVHen thou canſt not ſpeake in confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to edification, but feeleſt thine heart ſhut up, then apply, Joh. 7.38. <hi>Hee that beleeveth on me, out of his belly ſhall flow rivers of living water.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Prov. 10.31. <hi>The mouth of the juſt bringeth forth wiſedome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Prov. <hi>12.14. A man ſhall be ſatisfied with good by the fruit of his mouth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Iſai. <hi>32.4. The tongue of the ſtammerers ſhall be ready to ſpeake plainely.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Iſai. <hi>35.6. The dumbe mans tongue ſhall ſing.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:150899:86"/>
               <p> When thou art with the people of God, that thou maiſt receive good from them, and do them good, apply, Prov. 13.20. <hi>He that walketh with wiſe men ſhall bee wiſe.</hi> So ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, Prov. 12.14. John 7.38. Ezek. 47.12. <hi>His fruit ſhall bee meat, and his leaves medicine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If thou findeſt thy ſoule ſtand in need of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, keepe company with the people of God which are the only wiſe people, &amp; then thou haſt the only ſure promiſes of the Lord, thou ſhalt bee wiſe. If thou hungreſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter good, reſort to the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:150899:86"/>righteous, and thou ſhalt bee ſatisfied with good things. If thou feele thy ſelfe dead, apply, out of him ſhall flow rivers of water of life, for thy quickning. If thy ſoule be faint or ſicke, apply, his fruit ſhall be meat, &amp; his leaves medicine. Let all this good which is got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by their fellowſhip, cauſe thee to delight in them, and take heed of forſaking the fellowſhip of the Saints.</p>
               <p>When thou goeſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to company, apply theſe promiſes to thy ſelfe, that thou mayſt bee ſo to others, and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:150899:87"/>not thy ſelfe, by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleefe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>54.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHen thou art to goe to the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, to participate in the ordinances, apply,</hi> In places where I record my name, I will come to thee and bleſſe thee. <hi>If thou wanteſt the Lord or his bleſſing, go to his houſe, and thou ſhalt finde him. Pſal. 36.8, 9.</hi> They ſhall bee abundantly ſatisfied with the fatneſſe of thine houſe, and thou ſhalt make them drinke of the river of they pleaſures. For with thee
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:150899:87"/>is the fountaine of life, and in thy light ſhall wee ſee light. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65.4. Wee ſhall be ſatisfied with the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of thy houſe, even of then holy Temple. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 83.11. The lord God is a Sunne and ſhteld, the Lord will give grace and glory, and no good thing will hee withhold, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 92.13, 14. Thouſe that bee planted in the houſe of the Lord, ſhall flouriſh in the courts of our God. They ſhall ſtill bring forth fruit in their old age: they ſhall bee fat and ſtouriſhing. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 128.5. The Lord ſhall bleſſe thee out of Sion. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 25.6, 7, 8. In this mountaine
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:150899:88"/>ſhall the Lord of Hoſtes make unto all people a feaſt of fat things, a feaſt of Wine on the lees, of fat things full of marrow, of wines on the lees, well refi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. <hi>Therefore when his ordinances are corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with mens inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, then thou mayſt preſſe him with this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, that hee will give us wine fined and purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, even his pureſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, and moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable to our hearts, as wine is. And when there is little nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, becauſe their gifts are weake, urge him with this, that hee hath
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:150899:88"/>promiſed to make us a feaſt of fat things full of marrow; for I take this promiſe to bee meant of the Churches after Chriſt, verſe.</hi> 7. And he will deſtroy in this moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the face of the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring caſt over all people, and the vaile that is ſpread over all nations. <hi>Thy ſins that are too ſtrong for thee, bring them to the Lord in his ordinances, &amp; he will deſtroy them, though thou ſeeme to be covered with them, and they ſpread as a vaile upon thee, yet believe his promiſes, and all things ſhall bee poſſible
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:150899:89"/>unto thee. Iſai.</hi> 56.7. I will make them joyfull in mine houſe of prayer, their burnt offering, and their ſacrifices ſhall bee accepted upon mine altar. <hi>God will both give to them and accept from them their ſacrifices, as plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to him. 2 Chron 20.20.</hi> Beleeve his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, ſo ſhall yee proſper.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prov. 1.5</hi> A wiſe man will heare, and will increaſe learning, and a man of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding ſhall attaine unto wiſe counſels. <hi>Prov.</hi> 4.10.12. Heare and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive my ſayings, and the years of thy life ſhall bee many, when thou goeſt thy
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:150899:89"/>ſteps ſhall not be ſtrait, and when thou runneſt thou ſhalt not ſtumble. <hi>Marke 4.24.</hi> Vnto you that heare ſhall more be given. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 55.3, 11, 12. Encline your eares and come unto mee, heare and your ſoules ſhall live; and I will make an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Covenant with you, even the ſure mercies of <hi>David.</hi> My words ſhall accompliſh that which I pleaſe, and it ſhall proſper in the thing whereto I ſent it. Therefore yee ſhall goe forth with joy, and bee led forth with peace; the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines and the hils ſhall breake forth before you into ſinging, and all the
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:150899:90"/>trees of the field ſhall clap their hands. <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. in ſtead of the throne ſhall come up the firre-tree, and in ſtead of the bryer ſhall come up the mirtle tree; <hi>this force ſhall the word have in thine heart for planting of Grace, and deſtroying of ſinne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.7. They that dwell under his ſhadow ſhall returne, they ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive as the corne, and grow as the vine, the ſcent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſhall be as the vine in Lebanon. <hi>If thou ſhould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt returne, apply this,</hi> hee ſhall returne. <hi>If thou beeſt decayed, apply this.</hi> They ſhall revive as
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:150899:90"/>the corne. <hi>If thou would<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt flouriſh in grace, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply,</hi> They ſhall flouriſh as the vine. <hi>If thou would<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt bee a ſweet ſmelling ſavour in all places, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply,</hi> The ſcent thereof ſhall bee as the vine of Lebanon. <hi>Seeing all theſe good things come from the powerfull ordinances of the Lord, let us give him no reſt, till hee beſtow theſe bleſſings upon us; when the Paſtour of the people pronounceth the bleſſing, apply this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, Numb.</hi> 6.27. I will bleſſe thee.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="promise">
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:150899:91"/>
               <head>The <hi>55.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>WOuldeſt thou en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the ordinances of God, and a bleſſing upon them, apply. Jer. 31.14. <hi>I will ſatiate the ſouls of the Prieſts with fatneſſe, and my people ſhall be ſatisfied with good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Jer. 3.15. <hi>I will give you paſtours according to mine heart, which ſhall feed you with knowledge and underſtanding.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ezek. 34.26.27. <hi>And I will make them and the places round about my hill a bleſsing, and I will cauſe the ſhowres to come downe
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:150899:91"/>in his ſeaſon: there ſhall be ſhowres of bleſsing. And the tree of the field ſhall yeeld her increaſe, and the earth ſhall yeeld her fruit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe promiſes are both for Paſtor &amp; Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the Paſtor ſhall bee able to teach with know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, his ſoule ſhall bee repleniſhed with fatnes, his teaching ſhall bee as ſeaſonable ſhowers of bleſſing, that ſhall make the people fruitfull. The people muſt apply theſe promiſes, firſt that God would give them able Teachers, and that they may finde their miniſtry
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:150899:92"/>bleſſed unto them, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to theſe promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. That they may bee fed with knowledge and underſtanding, that they may bee ſatisfied with goodneſſe, &amp; that their teaching may bee ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſhowers of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to make them fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, as it is promiſed, that the trees ſhall yeeld their fruit. How much are Gods ordinances to be deſired, by which hee doth convay ſo many bleſſings unto his people? Let us give him no reſt, till he furniſh Jeruſalem with all her ordinances and officers.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="promise">
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:150899:92"/>
               <head>The <hi>56.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>IF thou enjoyeſt glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous graces, or meanes of grace, and feareſt the loſing of them, apply, Iſai. 4.5.6. <hi>Vpon all the glory ſhall bee a defence. And there ſhall be a Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle for a ſhadow in the day time from the heat, and for a place of refuge, and for a covert from ſtorme, and from raine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Iſai. 27, 3. <hi>I the Lord doe keepe it, I will water it every moment: leſt any hurt it, I will keepe it night and day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Iſai. 33.16 <hi>His place of defence ſhall be the muniti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of Rockes, bread ſhall
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:150899:93"/>be given him, his waters ſhall be ſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Haſt thou any glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous grace or meanes of grace? arme thy ſelfe with the power of God in his promiſes, for the Devill will uſe all his forces and ſubtilty, to deprive thee of them; haſt thou a glorious mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, and pure ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance or glorious graces beginne to ſpring in thine heart, and ſeeſt no meanes to defend them, apply, <hi>Vpon all thy glory hee ſhall bee a defence. His defence ſhall be a munition of Rockes.</hi> Seeſt thou an heart of ſinne in thy ſelfe,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:150899:93"/>or the rage of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, that cauſeth thee to ſeare the loſſe of them? apply, <hi>There ſhall bee a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering for a ſhadow in the day for the heat.</hi> Doth the devil raiſe up ſtorms? outwardly, perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? apply, <hi>The defence and covering ſhall bee a place of refuge, and cover for the ſtorme, and for the raine.</hi> Feareſt thou the ſubtilty of thine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, that unawares when thou thinkeſt not on them, they will ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe thee, and ſteale thy bleſſing from thee? ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, <hi>I the Lord doe keepe it
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:150899:94"/>night and day.</hi> If thou feareſt God will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue thus to thee, apply, <hi>I will water it every mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> not one moment, but he will be adding &amp; nouriſhing: <hi>bread ſhall be given him, and his waters ſhall bee ſure.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="57" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>57.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHen thou art ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed from Gods ordinances, apply theſe promiſes for thy returne, Iſai. 35.10.</hi> The ranſomed of the Lord ſhall returne, &amp; come to Sion with ſongs, and everlaſting joy upon their heads: they ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:150899:94"/>joy and gladneſſe, and ſorrow and ſighing ſhall flee away. <hi>Jer. 3.14.</hi> I will take you two of a family, and one of a City, and will bring you to Sion. <hi>Deut. 30.4.</hi> If any of thine bee driven out unto the out moſt parts of heaven, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence will the Lord thy God ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thee, and from thence will hee fetch thee. <hi>Ezek. 34.11.12, 13, 14, 15, 16.</hi> Behold I, even I will both ſearch my ſheepe, and ſeeke them out. As a ſheepheard ſeeketh out his ſtocke in the day that hee is among his ſheepe that are ſcattered: ſo will I ſeeke out my ſheepe, and will deliver them out
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:150899:95"/>of all places, where they have beene ſcattered in the cloudy and darke day. And I will bring them out from the people, and gather them from the countries, and will bring them to their owne land, and feed them upon the mountaines of Iſrael, by the riviers, and in all the inhabited places of the Country: I will feed them in a good paſture, and upon the high mountaines of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael ſhall their fold be: there ſhall they lie in a good fold, and in a fat paſture ſhal they feed upon the mountaines of Iſrael. I will feed my flocke, and I will cauſe them to lye down, ſaith the Lord God. I
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:150899:95"/>will ſeeke that which was loſt, and bring againe that which was driven away, &amp; wil binde up that which was broken, and will ſtrengthen that which was ſicke.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If thou now mourneſt for Gods ordinances, apply,</hi> Thou ſhalt not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly returne to Sion, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne with joy, and ſorrow ſhall flee away. <hi>If thou beeſt but one amongſt many which deſireſt it, and feareſt thou ſhalt be left among them, apply,</hi> I will take you one of a ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and two of a Tribe: <hi>though thou beeſt but one of a City that retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt to the Lord, he will
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:150899:96"/>bring thee to Sion from all the reſt. If thou art farre removed from all meanes, and that the Lord hath done it for thy ſinne, apply,</hi> Though thou were caſt into the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt part of the Heaven, thence will the Lord gather thee, and from thence will hee take thee; he will deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver from all places where they have beene ſcattered in the cloudy and dark day, and will feed them in good paſtures, and will bring them to reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="58" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>58.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>WHilſt thou art ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed from Gods
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:150899:96"/>houſe, apply, Ezek. 11.16 <hi>I will be unto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as a little Sanctuary in the countries where they ſhall come.</hi> Iſai. 40.11. <hi>Hee ſhall feede his flocke like a ſheepheard, hee ſhall gather the Lambes with his arme, and carrie them in his boſome, and ſhall gently lead thoſe that are with young.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In thy baniſhment, at thoſe houres when they ſoule was wont to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed in the Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, and at other times, when thou findeſt thy ſelfe to ſtand in need ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of defence, or nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment, apply, <hi>I will
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:150899:97"/>bee a Sanctuary unto you. Hee ſhall feed his flocke as a ſheepheard.</hi> If in this time thou feeleſt thy ſelfe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry weake, apply, <hi>Hee ſhall gather his Lambes in his armes, and carrie them in his boſome, and guide them with young:</hi> they cannot miſcarie that are ſhut up in the boſome of God: nor feare who are gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by him. Therefore though wee be never ſo weake in our ſelves, yet here is our comfort, wee are ſafe in our God: O happy people, ſaved by the Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="59" type="promise">
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:150899:97"/>
               <head>The <hi>59.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHen wicked ſheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards are over us, then apply, Ezek. 34.10.</hi> Thus ſaith the Lord God, Behold, I am againſt the ſheepheards, and I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire my flocke at their hand, and cauſe them to ceaſe from feeding the flock, neither ſhall the ſheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards feed themſelves any more: for I will deliver my flocke fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their mouth, that they may not bee meat for them. <hi>verſ. 21, 22.</hi> Becauſe yee have thruſt with ſide, &amp; with ſhoulder, and puſht all the diſeaſed with your hornes, till yee have ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:150899:98"/>them abroad: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will I ſave my flocke, and they ſhall no more bee a prey, and I will cauſe the wilde beaſt to ceaſe out of the land.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When the ſheepeards feed themſelves, and are ready to devoure us, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply,</hi> The ſheepheards ſhall not feed themſelves any, more. I will deliver my ſheepe from their mouther; they ſhall no more devoure them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When through their greatneſſe &amp; our weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, they puſh us ſo with their hornes, that wee are ſcattered, both ſheepheard from peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:150899:98"/>and one from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, apply,</hi> I will helpe my ſheep, and they ſhall no more bee ſpoiled; I will cauſe the wilde beaſts to ceaſe out of the land.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="60" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>60.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>WHen through evill ſhepheards we are come to great miſerie, apply, Ezek. 34.16. <hi>I will ſeeke that which was loſt, and bring againe that which was driven away, and will binde up that which was broken, and will ſtrengthen that which was ſicke.</hi> Iſai. 30.20. <hi>Though
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:150899:99"/>the Lord give you the bread of adverſitie, and the water of affliction, yet ſhall not thy teachers bee removed into a corner any more, but thine eyes ſhall ſee thy tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers.</hi> When through evill ſheepheards thou art come to ſuch an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate as thou feeleſt thy ſelfe to have loſt God and goodneſſe, and art driven away from all things that might helpe thee, apply, <hi>I will ſeeke that which was loſt, I will bring againe that which was driven away.</hi> When thou art even broken with miſery and growne very weake, apply, <hi>I will
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:150899:99"/>binde up that which was broken, and ſtrengthen that which was weake.</hi> When they Teachers which ſhould helpe thee in this eſtate, are forced to flie and hide themſelves for feare of wicked ſheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards, apply, <hi>Thy tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers ſhall not bee removed into a corner any more, but thine eyes ſhall ſee thy Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus farre of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of God, which are ordinary; Now for the duty of Faſting, which is extraordinary.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="61" type="promise">
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:150899:100"/>
               <head>The <hi>61.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>WHen thou ſetteſt thy ſelfe to faſt, apply, Mat. 6.18. <hi>If thou faſt in ſecret, thy father which ſeeth in ſecret will reward thee openly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Jam. 4.8.10. <hi>Draw nigh unto God, and hee will draw nigh unto you. Humble your ſelves in the ſight of the Lord, &amp; he ſhall lift you up.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus farre of the meanes of Grace, the next promiſes are when we ſuffer preſecution for well-doing, for all that will live godly muſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer perſecution: therefore ſtrengthen thy ſelfe with theſe promiſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="62" type="promise">
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:150899:100"/>
               <head>The <hi>62.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IF thou beeſt railed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for well doing, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, 1 Peter 4.14.</hi> If yee be reproached for the name of Chriſt, happy are yee, for the Spirit of God, and of glory refleth upon you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Matth. 5.11.12.</hi> Bleſſed are yee, when men ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile you, and perſecute you; and ſhall ſay all manner of evill againſt you falſly for my ſake. Rejoyce and be exceeding glad, for great is your reward in heaven, for ſo perſecuted they the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets which were before you.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="63" type="promise">
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:150899:101"/>
               <head>The <hi>63.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>WHen they perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute thee any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wayes even unto death, apply, Matth. 10. 39. <hi>He that loſeth his life for my ſake, ſhall finde it.</hi> Matth. 5.10. <hi>Bleſſed are they which are perſecuted for righteouſneſſe ſake: for theirs is the Kingdome of Heaven.</hi> When wee loſe any earthly bleſſing for Gods cauſe, apply, Mat. 19.24. <hi>Every one that hath forſaken houſes, or brethren, or ſiſters, or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or mother, or wife, or children, or lands for my
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:150899:101"/>names ſake, ſhall receive an hundred fold, and ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit everlaſting life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is the greateſt (&amp; yet lawfull) uſury of all others, to part with one outward bleſſing, and to receive an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth for it, to loſe a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable life, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy eternall life, to ſuffer a ſhort time, and to have a great reward in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, to bee diſgraced, and to have the Spirit of glory reſt upon us Therefore when thou art rayled upon, apply, <hi>Bleſſed am I, the Spirit of glory reſts upon mee, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they cannot make me
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:150899:102"/>vile.</hi> Art thou any way perſecuted? apply, <hi>theirs is the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; great is your reward in Heaven.</hi> Take they thy life? apply, <hi>Hee that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his life for my ſake ſhall finde it.</hi> Take they away any earthly bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing? thou ſhalt receive an hundreth fold at this preſent; therefore if V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurers gladly let out their money, that hope to receive but eight in the hundreth, bee aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of thy ſelfe, that thou ſhouldeſt not give one for an hundreth, when thou haſt the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of him that never
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:150899:102"/>failed to perfome.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="64" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>64.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>IN partaking with Gods people in ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, that thou mayſt bee partaker of their comforts, apply, 2 Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth. 1.6. <hi>As you are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the ſufferings: ſo ſhall yee bee alſo of the conſolation.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="65" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>65.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHen thou art cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led forth to defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the truth, apply, Matth. 10.19.</hi> When they deliver
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:150899:103"/>you up, take no thought, how, or what ye ſhall ſpeake, for it ſhall be given you in that ſame houre what yee ſhall ſpeake.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Luke 21.15.</hi> I will give you a mouth and wiſedome which all your adverſaries ſhall not be able to gaineſay nor reſiſt. <hi>Matth. 10.32.</hi> Whoſoever confeſſeth mee before men, him will I confeſſe before my Father which is in heaven. <hi>When thou feareſt thou ſhalt not bee able to ſpeake in defence of the truth, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply,</hi> It ſhall bee given thee, though thou haſt it not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, in that houre, what thou ſhalt ſay. <hi>If thou fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:150899:103"/>the learning of thine adverſaries, and thine owne ſimpleneſſe, apply,</hi> I will give thee not onely a mouth, but alſo wiſedome, where-againſt they ſhall not be able to ſpeake. <hi>If thou want courage, embol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den thy ſelfe with this, Chriſt will confeſſe thee before his father.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="66" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>66.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>IF thou wouldſt bring forth ſeaſonable fruit for every eſtate, and for every duty, apply, Pſal. 1.3. <hi>Thou ſhalt bee as a tree which bringeth forth
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:150899:104"/>his fruit in ſeaſon.</hi> Ezek. 47.12. <hi>Hee ſhall bring forth fruit according to his moneths.</hi> If thou art to ſpeake or pray, or doe any duty, that thou mayſt doe it ſeaſonably, and have fitting words and thoughts, apply, <hi>thou ſhalt bring forth fruit in ſeaſon.</hi> So in every e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, proſperity or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, that thou mayſt bring forth the fruits of it, apply, <hi>They ſhall bring forth fruit in ſeaſon, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their moneths.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus farre about ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall things. The next promiſes are about
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:150899:104"/>earthly things: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Children are the moſt excellent, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I will beginne with them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="67" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>67.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IF thou haſt children, apply, Pſal. 112.2.</hi> His ſeed ſhall be mighty upon earth: the generation of the juſt ſhall be bleſſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Deut. 7.13.</hi> Hee will bleſſe the fruit of thy womb. <hi>Gen. 17.7.</hi> I will eſtabliſh my covenant betweene mee and thee, and thy ſeed after thee, in their generations for an everlaſting cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, to be a God unto thee,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:150899:105"/>and to thy ſeed after thee. <hi>Iſai. 44.3, 4.</hi> I will poure my Spirit upon thy ſeed, and my bleſsing upon thine off ſpring: and they ſhall ſpring up as among the graſſe, as willowes by the water-courſes. <hi>If thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireſt grace and Gods bleſſing for thy children, apply,</hi> I will poure my Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and bleſsing upon thy ſeed. <hi>If thou wouldeſt have them grow up in it, apply,</hi> They ſhall grow as among the graſſe, and as the willowes by the water courſes. <hi>If thou wouldſt have them in the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with thy ſelfe, thy God to be theirs, apply,</hi>
                  <pb n="143" facs="tcp:150899:105"/>I will make an everlaſting covenant with thee, to bee God to thee, and to thy ſeed ofter thee. <hi>Deſireſt thou outward things for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? apply,</hi> His ſeed ſhall bee mighty upon earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="68" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>68.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IF thou wanteſt chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, apply, Deut 7.14.</hi> Thou ſhalt bee bleſſed above all people, there ſhall neither be male nor female barren among you. <hi>Deut. 28.11.</hi> The Lord ſhall make thee plentifull in the fruit of thy body <hi>Pſalm. 128.3.</hi> Thy wife ſhall bee as a fruitfull vine by the
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:150899:106"/>ſides of thine houſe, thy children like Olive plants, round about thy table. <hi>verſ. 4.6.</hi> Loe thus ſhall the man bee bleſſed that feareth the Lord. Thou ſhalt ſee thy childrens children.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If thou haſt concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, apply this promiſe for keeping of it, Exod. 23.26.</hi> There ſhall none caſt their young, nor bee barren in thy land. <hi>This, and all other promiſes of earthly things, are to bee applyed ſo farre as is good for us: wee are not to doubt of them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="69" type="promise">
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:150899:106"/>
               <head>The <hi>69.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IF the Lord deny thee children, apply, Iſai. 56.5.</hi> To them will I give in mine houſe, and within my walls, a place and a name better then of Sonnes and of Daughters, I will give them an everlaſting name that ſhall not be cut off.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="70" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>70.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IF thou wouldeſt have the comfortable and holy uſe of thine habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, apply, Iob. 5.24,</hi>
                  <pb n="146" facs="tcp:150899:107"/>Thou ſhalt know that thy Tabernacle ſhal be in peace, and thou ſhalt viſit thine habitation, and not ſinne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pſal. 91.10.</hi> There ſhall no evill befall thee, neither ſhall any plague come nigh thy dwelling. <hi>Prov. 14.11.</hi> The Takernacle of the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right ſhall flouriſh. <hi>Prov. 12.7.</hi> The houſe of the righteous ſhall ſtand.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If thou wouldeſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper in thine houſe, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply,</hi> Peace ſhall be in it. No plague ſhall come neare it. It ſhall flouriſh. <hi>If thou wouldeſt have it conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nne ſo; apply,</hi> It ſhall ſtand. <hi>That they may not bee a ſnare to thee,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:150899:107"/>but thou maiſt uſe thy bleſſing, and not ſinne, apply,</hi> Thou ſhalt viſit thy habitation, and not ſinne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="71" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>71.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IF thou wouldeſt have thy comming in and going out bloſſed, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, Deut. 28.6.</hi> Bleſſed ſhalt thou bee when thou commeſt in, and bleſſed ſhalt thou be when thou go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt out. <hi>Pſalm. 121.8.</hi> The Lord ſhall preſerve thy go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, out, and thy comming in; from this time forth, and even for evermore.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When thou goeſt out, if thou wouldeſt have
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:150899:108"/>the heavens and earth, and all creatures bleſſed to thee, and bee made able to make the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall uſe of them, apply,</hi> Bleſſed ſhalt thou bee when thou goeſt out, and when thou commeſt in. The Lord ſhal preſerve thy going out, and thy comming in. <hi>If thou wouldeſt haue the continuance of it, apply,</hi> From this time forth for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vermore.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="72" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>72.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>WHen thou eateſt or enjoyeſt any bleſſing, that it may ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:150899:108"/>thee, and thou mayeſt have the ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed uſe of it, apply, Ioel 2.26. <hi>Ye ſhall eate in plenty and be ſatisfied, and praiſe the name of the Lord your God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That thy meate and outward bleſſings may give thee content, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie thee, apply, <hi>Thou ſhalt eat and be ſatisfied.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That thou maiſt have the ſanctified uſe of it, apply, <hi>Thou ſhalt praiſe the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="73" type="promise">
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:150899:109"/>
               <head>The <hi>73.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>WHen thou takeſt thy reſt at night, apply, Prov. 3.24. <hi>When thou lyeſt downe thou ſhalt not bee afraid: yea thou ſhalt lie downe, and thy ſleepe ſhall be ſweet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Job. 11.19. <hi>Alſo thou ſhalt lie downe, and none ſhall make thee afraid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If thou art troubled with feares of the night, apply, <hi>Thou ſhalt not bee afraid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When thou takeſt thy reſt, apply, <hi>None ſhall make thee afraid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If thou art troubled
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:150899:109"/>with any thing that breakes thy reſt, apply, <hi>Thy reſt ſhall be ſweet.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="74" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>74.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>WHen thou putteſt thine hand to any worke, that it may bee bleſſed, apply, Deut. 28.12. <hi>The Lord ſhall bleſſe all the worke of thine hand.</hi> Deut. 30.9. <hi>The Lord thy God will make thee plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous in every worke of thine hand.</hi> The Lord will not onely bleſſe ſome of thy workes, but every one; therefore in every worke ſend up
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:150899:110"/>ſhort prayers for the clayming of them, and ſo at our going out, and comming in, or eating, or ſleeping, renew theſe promiſes upon thy ſelfe, by faith applying them, and by prayer ſuing for them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="75" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>75.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IF thou wouldeſt have thy outward bleſſings bleſſed of God, apply, Deut. 28.4, 5.</hi> Bleſſed ſhall bee the fruit of thy body, and the fruit of thy ground, and the fruit
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:150899:110"/>of thy cattell, the increaſe of thy kind, and the flockes of thy ſheepe. Bleſſed ſhall be thy basket and thy ſtore. <hi>Deut. 7.13, 14</hi> The Lord will alſo bleſſe the fruit of thy wombe, and the fruit of thy land, thy corne, and thy wine, and thine oyle, the encreaſe of thy Kine, and the flockes of thy ſheepe. There ſhall bee neither male or female barren a mong you, or among your cattell. <hi>That thy goods and thine houſe may be bleſſed, apply,</hi> Bleſſed ſhall bee thy basket and thy ſtore. <hi>If thou beeſt in debt, apply, Deuteron. 28.12.</hi> Thou ſhalt lend
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:150899:111"/>unto many, and ſhall not borrow.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="76" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>76.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IF thou deſireſt to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the labours of thine hands, apply, Iſai 65.21, 23, 23.</hi> They ſhall build houſes and inhabit them, they ſhall plant vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards and eate the fruit of them. They ſhall not build, and another inhabit; they ſhall not plant, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eate: for as the dayes of a tree are the dayes of my people, and mine elect ſhall long enjoy the workes of their hands. They ſhall
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:150899:111"/>not labour in vaine, nor bring forth for trouble. <hi>Pſ. 128.2</hi> Thou ſhalt cate the labour of thine hands.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="77" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>77.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHen thou art di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent in thy cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, apply, Prov, 12.14.24.</hi> The recompence of a mans hands ſhall bee rende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto him. The hand of the diligent ſhall beare rule. <hi>When thou enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt that thou haſt labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for, apply, Pſal. 128.2.</hi> thou ſhalt cate the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of thine hands: hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie ſhalt thou bee, andre ſhall be well with thee.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="78" type="promise">
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:150899:112"/>
               <head>The <hi>78.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHen thou ſeeſt the wicked to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with reſtleſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, hungring and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting after thoſe things which ſatisfie them not, and thou deſireſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, apply, Iſaiah 65 13, 14.</hi> Thus ſaith the Lord, behold my ſervants ſhall cate, but yee ſhall be hungry: behold my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants ſhall drinke, but yee ſhall be thirſty, behold my ſervants ſhall rejoyce, but yee ſhall be aſhamed: Behold my ſervants ſhall ſing for joy of heart, but ye ſhall cry for ſorrow of heart, and
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:150899:112"/>ſhall howle for vexation of ſpirit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="79" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>79.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IF thou feareſt thou ſhalt loſe by follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lord, apply, Pſal. 37.9, 11, 18, 19,</hi> Thoſe that waite upon the Lord ſhall inherit the earth, their inheritance ſhall be for ever: they ſhall not be aſhamed in the evill time. They ſhall inherit the earth, and delight themſelves in the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of peace. <hi>Pſal. 112.3.</hi> Wealth and riches ſhall bee in his huſe. <hi>Iob 22.23,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:150899:113"/>24.</hi> Thou ſhalt bee built up, thou ſhalt lay up gold as duſt, &amp; the gold of Ophir as the ſtones of the brookes. <hi>verſe 25.</hi> Yea, the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty ſhall be thy defence, and thou ſhalt have plenty of ſilver.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gen. 15.1.</hi> I am thy excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding great reward, <hi>Feareſt thou the loſſe of thy land, apply,</hi> Thou ſhalt inherit the earth, their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance ſhall bee for ever. Thou ſhalt poſſeſſe the Earth. <hi>Doe others trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thee? apply,</hi> They ſhall have their delight in the multitude of peace. <hi>Art thou poore or fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt the loſſe of thy
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:150899:113"/>goods? apply,</hi> Riches and taeaſure ſhal be in his houſe. <hi>Art thou oppreſſed by the wicked? apply,</hi> The Almighty ſhall bee thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="80" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>80.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHen thou haſt loſt bleſſings by ſinne, apply theſe promiſes for their recovery, Joel. 2.24, 25, 26.</hi> The floores ſhall bee full of wheat, and the fats ſhall overflow with wine and oyle, and I will reſtore to you the yeares that the Locuſt hath eaten, the cankerworme, the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpiller,
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:150899:114"/>and the palmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worme: and yee ſhall eat in plenty, and be ſatisfied, and praiſe the Lord. <hi>Deut. 20.5.</hi> I will multiplie you above your fathers.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="81" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>81.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IF thou feareſt the loſſe of thy good name, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, Iob, 5.21.</hi> Thou ſhalt be hid from the ſcourge of the tongue. <hi>Iob. 11.15.</hi> Thou ſhalt lift up thy face without ſpot. <hi>Pſal. 37.6.</hi> He ſhall bring forth thy righteouſneſſe as the light, and thy judgment as the noone day. <hi>Prov. 10.7.</hi>
                  <pb n="161" facs="tcp:150899:114"/>The memory of the juſt is bleſſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Feareſt thou the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked will take away thy good name? apply,</hi> Thou ſhalt bee hid from the ſcourge of the tongue. <hi>Caſt they blots upon thee? apply,</hi> Thou ſhalt lift up thy face without ſpot. <hi>Seeke they to darken the light of thy holy life? apply,</hi> He ſhall bring forth thy righteouſneſſe as the light, and thy judgement as the noone day.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="82" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>82.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IF the World deſpiſe thee, comfort thy ſelfe
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:150899:115"/>with theſe promiſes, Ex. 19.5.</hi> Yee ſhall be Gods peculiar treaſure above all people. <hi>1. Sam. 3.30.</hi> Thoſe that honor me will I honor, ſaith the Lord. <hi>Pſal. 91.14.</hi> I will ſet him on high, beauſe he hathy knowne my name. <hi>Pſalm. 112.9.</hi> His horne ſhall bee exalted with honour. <hi>John 12.26.</hi> If any man ſerve me, him will my Father honour. <hi>Prov. 4.7, 8, 9.</hi> Get wiſedome, exalt her, and ſhe ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote thee, Shee ſhall bring thee to honour when thou doſt embrace her; Shee ſhall give to thine head an orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of grace, a crowne of glory ſhall ſhee deliver to thee.</p>
               <pb n="163" facs="tcp:150899:115"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>When the world counts thee as the off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcouring of the world, vile, nought-worth: ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply,</hi> Ye ſhall be Gods chiefe treaſure above all people. <hi>Doth the world debaſe thee? apply.</hi> The Lord will exapt thee. The Father will honour him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="83" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>83.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHen thou art in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny want for ſoule, or body, apply, Pſal. 34.9.10.</hi> There is no want to them that feare him. The young Lions doe lacke and ſuffer hunger, but they that ſeeke the Lord ſhall not
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:150899:116"/>want any good thing. <hi>Pſal. 84.11.</hi> No good thing will hee with hold from them that walke uprightly. <hi>Mat. 6.33.</hi> Seeke ye firſt the Kingdome of God and his righteouſneſſe, and all theſe things ſhall be added unto you. <hi>Art thou troubled with diſtracting cares for outward things? apply,</hi> Seeke the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heaven and his righteouſneſſe, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things ſhall be caſt upon you. <hi>Feareſt thou that thou ſhalt bee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verpreſſed with want? apply,</hi> Thoſe that ſeeke the Lord, ſhall want no good thing. No good thing
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:150899:116"/>will he withhold from-them that walke uprightly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="84" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>84.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IN liberall giving, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply theſe promiſes, Prov. 11.25.</hi> The liberall ſoule ſhall be made fat, and he that watreth ſhall be wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred alſo himſelfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prov. 19.17.</hi> He that hath pittie on the poore, len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to the Lord: and that which he hath given will he pay him againe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Math. 6.4.</hi> Givein ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, and thy Father him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſhall reward thee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly. <hi>2. Cor. 9.6.10.11.</hi> Hee which ſoweth bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:150899:117"/>ſhall reape bountiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. He that miniſtreth ſeed to the ſower, doth miniſter bread for your food, and multiply your ſeed ſowne, and increaſe the fruits of your righteouſneſſe, being inriched in every thing to all bountifulneſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſai. 58.10.11.</hi> If thou draw out thy ſoule to the hungry, and ſatisfie the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted foule: then ſhall thy light riſe in obſcurity, and thy darkeneſſe bee as the noone day. And the Lord ſhall guide thee continually, and ſatisfie thy ſoule in drought, and make fat thy bones, and thou ſhalt bee like a watred garden, and
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:150899:117"/>like aſpring of waters, whoſe waters faile not.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When thou giveſt to the people of God, and entreateſt them kindly, apply, Matth. 10.41, 42.</hi> He that receiveth a Prophet in the name of a Prophet, ſhall receive a Prophets re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards and he that receiveth a righteous man, in the name of a righteous man, ſhall receive a righteous mans reward. And who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſocver ſhall give to drirke unto one of theſe little ones a cup of cold water onely in the name of a Diſciple, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily I ſay unto you, hee ſhall in no wiſe loſe his reward.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="85" type="promise">
               <pb n="168" facs="tcp:150899:118"/>
               <head>The <hi>85.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IF ſickneſſe be amongſt us, apply, Exod. 23.52.</hi> I will take ſickneſſe away from the midſt of thee.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pſal. 41.3.</hi> The Lord will ſtrengthen him upon the bed of languiſhing; thou wilt make all his bed in his ſickneſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Deut. 7.15.</hi> And the Lord will take away from thee all ſickneſſe, and will put none of the evill diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Egypt upon thee.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If the plague bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, apply, Pſalm. 91.3.6, 7.</hi> Surely he ſhall deliver thee from the noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome peſtilence. Thou ſhalt
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:150899:118"/>not bee afraid of the peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence that walketh in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, nor for the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that waſteth at noon day. A thouſand ſhall fall at thy ſide, and ten thouſand at thy right hand: but it ſhall not come nigh thee.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Art thou ſicke? apply,</hi> The Lord will ſtrengthen him upon the bed of ſorrow: thou wilt make all his bed in his ſickeneſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Art thou there where the ſicke are? apply,</hi> I will take away all ſickneſſe from the midſt of thee.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Feareſt thou the peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence? apply,</hi> I will deliver thee frrom the noyſome pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="86" type="promise">
               <pb n="170" facs="tcp:150899:119"/>
               <head>The <hi>86.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>IF thou feareſt death, apply, Iſai. 57.2. <hi>He ſhal enter into peace, they ſhall reſt in their beds.</hi> None feares to go to bed, when they know they ſhal reſt, being weary. This reſting is more ſure and laſting for ever. Rom. 8.11. <hi>Hee that raiſed vp Chriſt from the dead, ſhall quicken your mortall bodies.</hi> Therefore we muſt not thinke of it, but as a better life given by the Spirit of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="87" type="promise">
               <pb n="171" facs="tcp:150899:119"/>
               <head>The <hi>87.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IF thou feareſt untimely death, apply, Iob. 5.26.</hi> thou ſhalt come to thy grave in a full age, like as a ſhocke of corne commeth in, in his ſeaſon. <hi>Exod. 23.26.</hi> The number of thy daies will I fulfil. <hi>Pſalme 91.16.</hi> With long life will I ſatisfie him, and ſhew him my ſalvation <hi>Pſal. 41.2.</hi> The Lord will preſerue him and keepe him alive, and he ſhall be bleſſed upon the earth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Haſt thou many ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and feareſt the loſſe of thy Life by them?
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:150899:120"/>apply,</hi> the number of thy daies wil I fulfill: <hi>the Lord wil preſerve him &amp; keep him alive, therefore man cannot ſhorten it one day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Feareſt thou that thou ſhalt either live too lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, or die too ſoone? apply,</hi> Thou ſhalt goe to thy grave in a full age, as a ricke of corne commeth in due ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon into the barne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="88" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>88.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IF thou feareſt hurt by any of the creatures, apply, Gen. 9.2.</hi> The feare of you and the dread of you
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:150899:120"/>ſhall be vpon every beaſt of the earth, and upon every fowle of the ayre, upon all that moveth upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the earth, upon all the fiſhes of the ſea, into your hand are they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, <hi>Job. 5.23.</hi> Thou ſhalt be in league with the ſtones of the field: and the beaſt of the field ſhall be at peace with thee.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="89" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>89.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>WHen thine heart is troubled either for ſoule or body, apply, Phil. 4.7. <hi>The peace of God which paſſeth all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, ſhall keepe your
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:150899:121"/>hearts and minder</hi> Pſal. 29 11, <hi>The Lord will bleſſe his people with peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is thine heart troubled with many temptations of Satan, or with feares of ſin and miſery? apply, <hi>the peace of GOD ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve your hearts.</hi> Haſt thou many troubles out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly? ap. <hi>the Lord ſhalt bleſſe his people with peace.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="90" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>90.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>IF thou wouldeſt have thy purpoſes to proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, apply, Iob. 22.28. <hi>Thou ſhalt alſo decree a thing, and it ſhall be eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed unto thee: and the
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:150899:121"/>light ſhall ſhine upon thy wayes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Pſal. 1.3. <hi>Whatſoever he doth ſhall proſper.</hi> Pſal. 37.5. <hi>Commit thy way unto the Lord: truſt alſo in him, and he ſhal bring it to paſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When thou often pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeſt to do good both for thy ſoule and body, and yet findeſt thy pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes broken, apply, <hi>Thou ſhalt decree A thing, and the Lord ſhall ſtabliſh it unto thee. He ſhall bring it to paſſe.</hi> When thou art in doing of any thing, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, <hi>Whatſoever he doth ſhall proſper.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="91" type="promise">
               <pb n="176" facs="tcp:150899:122"/>
               <head>The <hi>91.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>When thou art cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to a great worke, wherein thou ſhalt have great oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, apply, Deut. 31.8. <hi>The Lord he it is that doth goe before thee, he will bee with thee, he will not faile thee, neither forſake thee: feare not, neither be diſmai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> 2 Chron. 16.9. <hi>The Lord will ſhew himſelfe ſtrong in the behalfe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whoſe heart is perfect to wards him:</hi> Pſal. 91.11, 12 13. <hi>He ſhall give his Angels charge over thee, to keepe thee in all thy waies: They ſhall beare thee up in their
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:150899:122"/>hands, leſt thou daſh thy foote againſt a ſtone. Thou ſhalt treade upon the Lion and Adder: The young Lion and Dragon ſhalt thou tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple under feet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It maters not what be the lets to oppoſe us, when the Lord goes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us, hee will eaſily beat them downe: nor what ſtrength reſiſts ſuch, as hee hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſhew his ſtrength for: nor how many bee our dangers, when his Angels have charge o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us to keepe us. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore go on in the worke, and feare not the iſſue, being ſtrengthned by the
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:150899:123"/>promiſes of him, that never faileth his.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="92" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>92.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IN the time of danger, apply, 1 Sam. 2.9.</hi> The Lord will keepe the feet of his Saints. <hi>Pro. 1.33.</hi> Who ſo harkneth unto me ſhall dwell ſafely, &amp; ſhall be qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et from feare of evill. <hi>Iob. 11.18, 19.</hi> Thou ſhalt be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, becauſe there is hope, yea thou ſhalt digge about thee, and thou ſhalt take thy reſt in ſafety, alſo thou ſhalt lie downe, and none ſhall make thee afraid. <hi>Pſal. 125 1, 2.</hi> They which truſt in
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:150899:123"/>the Lord, ſhall bee as mount Sion which cannot be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, but abideth for ever. As the mountaines are rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d about Ieruſalem: ſo the Lord is round about his people from henceforth, even for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pſal. 121.3, 4, 5.</hi> He will not ſuffer thy foot to be moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: be that keepeth thee will not ſlumber. Behold he that keepeth Iſrael will nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſlumber nor ſleepe. The Lord is thy keeper, the Lord is thy ſhade vpon thy right hand. <hi>Seeing the Lord is our keeper, wee need not feare the danger.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="93" type="promise">
               <pb n="180" facs="tcp:150899:124"/>
               <head>The <hi>93.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHen thou art in great trouble, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply; Iſai. 43.2.</hi> When thou paſſeſt through the waters I will bee with thee, and through the Rivers, they ſhall not over flow thee: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou walkeſt through the fire, thou ſhalt not be burnt, neither ſhall the flame kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle upon thee. <hi>verſ. 20.</hi> I wil give waters in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and rivers in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſart, to give drinke to my people, my choſe. <hi>Pſal. 32.6, 7.</hi> Surely in the flood's of great waters, they ſhall not come nigh unto him. Thou art my hiding place, thou
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:150899:124"/>ſhalt preſerve mee fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; thou ſhalt compaſſe me about with ſongs of delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When thou ſeeſt thy ſelfe compaſſed with many troubles, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneſt to feare? apply,</hi> I will bee with thee, they ſhall not over flow thee. <hi>In the fire of affliction, thou ſhalt not onely not be burnt, but the flame ſhall not kindle upon thee, the greateſt trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles ſhall not doe thee the leaſt harme, for God being with thee, will bring thee out, as he did Iſraell through the ſea,
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:150899:125"/>and the three children out of the fire, with not ſo much as the ſavour of fire about them: ſo ſhall not ſo much as the ſavour of evill be upon his, but he will compaſſe them about with ſongs of deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="94" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>94.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou ſeemeſt to bee forgotten in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, apply, Pſal. 9.9.18.</hi> The Lord alſo will be a refuge for the oppreſſed: a refuge in times of trouble. For the needy ſhall not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way be forgotten: the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:150899:125"/>of the poore ſhall not periſh for ever.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſa. 49.15.</hi> Can a woman forget her ſucking child, that ſhe ſhold not have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsion on the ſonne of her wombe? yea, they may for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get, yet wil not I forget thee <hi>Pſal. 103.9.</hi> He will not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes chide: neither will he keepe his anger for ever. <hi>Lament. 3.31, 32.</hi> The Lord will not caſt off for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. But though he cauſe griefe, yet will he have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsion, according to the multitude of his mercies.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="95" type="promise">
               <pb n="184" facs="tcp:150899:126"/>
               <head>The <hi>95.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>WHen thou feareſt thou ſhalt end thy dayes in miſery, apply, Job. 36.11. <hi>They ſhall ſpend their dayes in proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and their years in plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="96" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>96.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHen thy ſorrowes grow great, apply Job. 11.16.</hi> That ſhalt forget thy miſerie, and re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>member it as waters that paſſe away. <hi>Job. 8.20, 21.</hi> Behold, God will not cast a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:150899:126"/>a perfect man, till hee fill thy mouth with laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and thy lips with rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing. <hi>Pſa. 27.14.</hi> Be of good courage, and he ſhall ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then thy heart, <hi>Pſal, 112.4.</hi> Vnto the upright there ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth light in the darkeneſſe. <hi>Pſal. 126.5, 6.</hi> They that ſow in teares ſhall reape in joy. He that goeth forth and weepeth, bearing precious ſeed, ſhall doubt leſſe come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine with rejoycing, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his ſheaves with him.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 10.28.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The hope of therighteous ſhalbe glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mat. 5.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Bleſſed are they that mourne, for they
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:150899:127"/>ſhall be comforted.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>John 16.22.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Yee now have ſorrow: but I will ſee you againe, and your hearts ſhall rejoyce, and your joy no man taketh from you.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hath ſorrow taken deep roote in thy ſoule, that thou feareſt thou ſhalt never finde hearty joy? apply,</hi> Hee ſhall comfort thine heart. <hi>Is ſuch a croſſe upon thee, that thou fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt thou ſhalt never for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get it? apply,</hi> thou ſhalt forget thy miſery, as waters that paſſe away.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="97" type="promise">
               <pb n="187" facs="tcp:150899:127"/>
               <head>The <hi>97.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>WHen thou art in ſuch an eſtate, as thou knoweſt no way out of miſerie, either for ſoule or body, or both, apply, Ier. 33.3. <hi>Call unto mee, and I will anſwer thee, and ſhew thee great and mighty things which thou knoweſt not.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="98" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>98.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IF thou wouldeſt have deliverance out of trouble, apply, Pſal. 149.4.</hi>
                  <pb n="188" facs="tcp:150899:128"/>He wil beautifie the meek with ſalvation: <hi>or, He wil make the meek glorious by deliverance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pſ. 34.17.19.</hi> The righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous crie, &amp; the Lord hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth: and delivereth them out of all their troubles. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are the afflictions of the righteous: but the Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livereth him out of them al. <hi>Job. 5.17, 18, 19.</hi> Happy is the man whom God corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth for he maketh ſore &amp; bindeth up: he woundeth, &amp; his hands make whole. Hee ſhall deliver thee in ſixe troubles, in ſeaven there ſhall no evill touch thee. <hi>Pſ. 50.15.</hi> Call upon mee in the day of trouble: I will deliver
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:150899:128"/>thee, and thou ſhalt glorifie mee.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>When thou art in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny troubles, and feareſt thou ſhalt never get out of all, apply,</hi> The Lord will deliver thee out of al. <hi>If the Lord hath delivered thee once or twice, and thou feareſt he wil not conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue ſo ſtill, as often as thou falleſt into troubles ap.</hi> He ſhall deliver thee in ſixe troubles, and the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth it ſhal not touch thee.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="99" type="promise">
               <pb n="190" facs="tcp:150899:129"/>
               <head>The <hi>99.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WHen thine enemies prevaile, apply, Pſ. 125.3.</hi> The rod of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſhal not reſt upon the lot of the righteous: leſt the righteous put forth their hands unto iniquitie: <hi>Pſal. 18.3.</hi> I will call upon the Lord: ſo ſhall I be ſaved from mine enemies, <hi>1 Sam 2.10.</hi> The adverſaries of the Lord ſhall be broken to pieces: the eies of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſhall faile, their refuge ſhall periſh, their hope ſhall be ſorrow of minde. <hi>Job. 11 20. Deut. 28.7.</hi> The Lord ſhall cauſe thine enemies
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:150899:129"/>that riſe up againſt thee, to be ſmitten before thy face.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seeſt thou many to riſe up to trouble thee? apply,</hi> thine enemies that riſe againſt thee, ſhall fall before thy face. <hi>Hope they to prevaile againſt thed? apply,</hi> their hope ſhall be ſorrow of minde: <hi>Have they great meanes to cauſe them to proſper? apply,</hi> their refuge ſhall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh. <hi>Have they long oppreſſed thee? apply,</hi> the rod of the wicked ſhall not alwaies reſt upon the lot of the righteous. <hi>Seeſt thou no meanes to get
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:150899:130"/>from them? ſay with the Prophet</hi> David, will call upon the Lord, ſo ſhall I bee ſafe from mine enemies.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="100" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>100.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THat thou maieſt be delivered, and thine enemies afflicted in thy ſtead, apply, Deut. 30.7.</hi> The Lord thy God will put all theſe curſes upon thine enemies, and on them that hate thee, which perſecute thee. <hi>Prov. 21.18.</hi> The wicked ſhall bee a ran ſome for the righteous, and the tranſgreſſour for the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="101" type="promise">
               <pb n="193" facs="tcp:150899:130"/>
               <head>The <hi>101.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IF thou wouldeſt have thine enemies deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, apply, Job. 8.22.</hi> They that hate thee ſhall be cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed with ſhame, and the dwelling place of the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſhal come to naught.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſaiah 41.11.13.15.</hi> Behold, all they which were incenſed againſt thee ſhall bee aſhamed and confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, they ſhall be as nothing, and they that ſtrive with thee ſhall periſh: for I the Lord thy God will hold thy right hand, ſaying unto thee, Feare not, I will helpe thee. Thou ſhalt threſh the
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:150899:131"/>mountaines and beat them ſmall, and ſhalt make the hils as chaffe, <hi>by which mountaines and hils, is meant the greateſt ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. 1. Sam. 2.30.</hi> They that deſpiſe mee ſhall bee lightly eſteemed. <hi>Theſe promiſes are to be apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by us, as they are the enemies of God and his Goſpell, and ours for his ſake.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="102" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>102.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IF the wicked plot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, apply, Pſal. 37.12.</hi> The wicked plot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the juſt; their ſword
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:150899:131"/>ſhall enter into their owne heart, their bow ſhall be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. The Lord ſhall laugh at him. <hi>Iſai. 54.15.</hi> The e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies ſhall ſurely gather themſelves together againſt thee, but not by me; whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhall gather themſelves together againſt thee ſhall fall.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="103" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>103.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>IN the troubles of the Church, apply, Pſalme 128.6. <hi>Thou ſhalt ſee peace upon Iſrael, Thou ſhalt ſee the good of Ieruſalem all the dayes of thy life.</hi> Jer. 31.12. <hi>Thou
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:150899:132"/>ſhalt come and ſing in the height of Sion:</hi> when thou haſt applyed the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and uſed all the meanes, and yet findeſt not thy ſelfe filled with God, as thou deſireſt, then comfort thy ſelfe with this, <hi>Yet is little while, and when thou awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt, thou ſhalt be ſatisfied with his image.</hi> Pſal. 17.15.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="104" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>104</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>BEcauſe the time draweth neere of the fall of Antichriſt, wee muſt ſtirre up our ſelves
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:150899:132"/>to haſten the Lord by earneſt prayers, and for the ſtrengthning of our faith, apply theſe promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Rev. 17.16.</hi> And the ten horned which thou ſaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt upon the Beaſt, theſt ſhall hate the Whore, and ſhall make here deſolate and naked, and ſhall cate her fleſh, and ſhall burne her with fire, <hi>Reu. 18.8.21.</hi> Therefore ſhall her plagues come in one day, death and mourning, and famine, and ſhe ſhall be utterly burnt with fire, for ſtrong is the Lord God who judgeth her. And a mighty Angell tooke up a great ſtone, like a great Milſtone, and caſt it
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:150899:133"/>into the Sea ſaying, Thus with violence ſhall that great City Babylon bee throwne downe, and ſhall be found no more at all, <hi>Even ſo down Lord Joſus, and hallen this happie day.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="105" type="promise">
               <head>The <hi>105.</hi> Legacie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SEEing the Lord hath promiſed many glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous things to the Jewes, with much grace and pouce, both to the Jewes so Gentiles at their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion; when the tonne tribes ſhall bee reunited to the two, which never
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:150899:133"/>yet was, let us never give him reſt till he ſet up Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem the praiſe of the world, and for the ſtrengthning of us in prayer, apply, theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes: Ezek. 37.21, 22.</hi> Thus ſaith the Lord God, Behold, I will take the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael, from among the heathen, whither they be gone, and will gather them on every ſide, and bring them into their owne land: and I will make them one nation, in the land upon the mountaines of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael: and one King ſhall bee King to them all, and they ſhall be no more two Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, neither ſhall they bee
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:150899:134"/>divided into two kingdoms any more at all, <hi>Jer. 3.18.</hi> In thoſe dayes the houſe of Iudah ſhall walke with the houſe of Iſrael, and they ſhall come together out of the land of the North to the land that I have given for an inheritance unto your fathers: <hi>Iſaiah 60.2, 3, 4, 5, 15, 16.</hi> The Lord ſhall ariſe upon thee, and his glory ſhall be ſeene upon thee. And the Gentiles ſhall come to the light, and Kings to the brightneſſe of thy riſing, thy ſonnes ſhall come from farre, and thy daughters ſhall bee nurſed at thy ſide, then thou ſhalt ſee and flow together, and
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:150899:134"/>thine heart ſhall feare and be enlarged, becauſe the Sea ſhall bee converted unto thee: the forces of the Gentiles ſhall come unto thee. Whereas thou haſt beene forſaken and hated, ſo that no man went through thee, I will make thee an eternall excellencie, a joy of many generations: Thou ſhalt alſo ſucke the milke of the Gentiles, and ſhalt ſucke the breaſt of Kings. <hi>Iſaiah 62.2, 3, 49.</hi> The Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles ſhall ſee thy righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and all Kings thy glory, and thou ſhalt be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by a new name, which the mouth of the Lord
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:150899:135"/>ſhalt name, thou ſhalt alſo bee a crowne of glory in the hand of the Lord, and a roy all diadem in the hand of thy God. <hi>Iſaiah 61.4, 5, 6.</hi> They ſhall build the old waſtes, they ſhall raiſe up the former deſolations, they ſhall repaire the waſt Cities the deſolations of many ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations. And ſtrangers ſhall ſtand and feed your flockes, and the ſonnes of the alien ſhall be your plow-men, and your vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſers, but yee ſhall bee na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the prieſts of the Lord: men ſhall call you the mint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of our God, yee ſhall cate the riches of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, and in their glory ſhall
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:150899:135"/>you boaſt your ſelves. <hi>Iſaiah 49.22, 23.</hi> Thus ſaith the Lord. Behold, I will lift up my hand to the Gentiles, &amp; ſet up my ſtandard to the people, and they ſhall bring thy ſons in their armes, and thy daughters ſhall be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried upon their ſhoulders, and Kings ſhall be thy nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing fathers, and their Queenes thy nurſing mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, they ſhall bow down to thee with their face towards the earth, and licke up the duſt of thy feet.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:150899:136"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150899:136"/>
            <p>THeſe promiſes I have obſerved: many more there bee of moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent uſe, but becauſe they need opening for the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of them, I would not ſet them downe, leſt through the ſhallowneſſe of my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding I ſhould wrong the precious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes: but I picked out the moſt plaine, and thoſe that I found of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall uſe for Soule and Body, which I have found much good by, for the promiſes are our Legacies bequeathed to us in the will of our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb facs="tcp:150899:137"/>&amp; wee are to claime them, as wee ſtand in need of any of them: and ſurely that God which would not have children wronged in that which is bequeathed to them in the will of their fathers, much leſſe will he with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold that which his Son hath bequeathed to us in his laſt will, which he ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with his blood. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let us ſue for them, for the ſaith, hee will bee ſought to, to performe them to us. And when thou applyeſt any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, ſeeke unto the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and labour to keepe it, and doubt not
<pb facs="tcp:150899:137"/>of the performance of what is promiſed, for he is both able and faithfull that hath promiſed.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:150899:138"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150899:138"/>
            <head>A TABLE FOR THE right and ready finding out of any Promiſe in this Booke, for the comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſupplie of preſent neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie: the number ſhewes the page, where the Promiſe (wee would have) is to bee found.</head>
            <list>
               <item>RVles for reading the Promiſes.</item>
               <item>If wee finde nothing in our ſelves that may move God. pag. <hi>1.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If wee feare God will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member our ſinnes, to puniſh them pag. <hi>5</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If often ſuing cauſe thee
<pb facs="tcp:150899:139"/>doubt of pardon. pag. <hi>6</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou deſpaire. pag. <hi>7</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou findeſt ſin an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy burden, and Satan pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing. pag. <hi>10</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou turne from ſinne, and yet doubt of pardon. pag. <hi>13</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou wouldeſt have thy many felt rebellions ſubdued pag. <hi>16</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thy heart be hard and full of corruption. pag. <hi>18</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If unbridled nature break out into paſsion. pag. <hi>20</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou be in bondage to ſome ſinne. pag. <hi>22</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou feareſt the break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of ſtrong ſinnes. pag. <hi>23</hi>
               </item>
               <item>When thou art ſtayed from ſinne by admonition pag. <hi>26</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:150899:139"/>
               <item>If thou feareſt God will deſtroy thee for ſinne pag. <hi>27</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou be tempted to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe pag. <hi>28</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou cauſt not finde out thy ſin, for which God cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects thee. pag. <hi>29</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou doubt of ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. pag. <hi>30</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thine heart bee as a wilderneſſe, barren of good, pag. <hi>31</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou wanteſt holineſſe, pag. <hi>37</hi>
               </item>
               <item>When thou canſt not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer up any ſacrifice pag. <hi>38</hi>
               </item>
               <item>When thou feeleſt but little grace pag. <hi>40</hi>
               </item>
               <item>When all thy graces are weake pag. <hi>41</hi>
               </item>
               <item>When thy heart is drie
<pb facs="tcp:150899:140"/>for want of grace. pag. <hi>41</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou wanteſt the ſpirit pag. <hi>45</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If looking on Gods love, thou canſt not love God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine pag. <hi>48</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou canſt not bring thine heart to delight in the Lord <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou ſeeleſt not Gods feare in thine heart pag. <hi>53</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thine heart wil not praiſe the Lord pag. <hi>54</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou wanteſt wiſdome pag. <hi>56</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou canſt not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand Gods voyce pag. <hi>57</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou canſt not ſee into the myſteries of the Goſpell pag. <hi>58</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou ſeeſt a good way
<pb facs="tcp:150899:140"/>and haſt no power to walke in it pag. <hi>59</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou wanteſt memory. pag. <hi>62</hi>
               </item>
               <item>When thou ſeeſt thine ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance. pag. <hi>68</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou deſireſt grace &amp; art not ſatisfied pag. <hi>68</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thine heart bee dead pag. <hi>70</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou feareſt falling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way pag. <hi>72</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou art falne pag. <hi>76</hi>
               </item>
               <item>When the Lord hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken thee pag. <hi>78</hi>
               </item>
               <item>When thou feeleſt thy vilenes. pag. <hi>81</hi>
               </item>
               <item>When thou feeleſt thy ſpirituall poverty pag. <hi>83</hi>
               </item>
               <item>When thou art in a ſtrait pag. <hi>85</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:150899:141"/>
               <item>If thou feareſt Satan wil cauſe thee to fall. pag. <hi>88</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou canſt not profit by the word of God pag. <hi>90</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou findeſt thy ſelfe unlike Gods people pag. <hi>91</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou wouldeſt have Gods bleſsing reſt upon thee pag. <hi>92</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou wouldeſt be a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in thy place. pag. <hi>94</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou ſeparateſt from the wicked in their corrupt worſhip. ib.</item>
               <item>A promiſe to be applied in every ordinance pag. <hi>96</hi>
               </item>
               <item>When thou prayeſt pag. <hi>97</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou meditateſt. pag. <hi>99</hi>
               </item>
               <item>In meditating, confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, reading Gods word pag. <hi>101</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:150899:141"/>
               <item>In reading of the word if thou underſtandeſt not pag. <hi>102</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou canſt not conferre pag. <hi>103</hi>
               </item>
               <item>When thou art to goe to the aſſemblies, pag. <hi>106</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Wouldeſt thou enjoy the ordinances of God, and a bleſsing upon them pag. <hi>114</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou enjoyeſt grace or meanes of grace pag. <hi>117</hi>
               </item>
               <item>When thou art baniſhed from Gods ordinances pag. <hi>120</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Whilſt thou art baniſht from Gods houſe pag. <hi>124</hi>
               </item>
               <item>When wicked ſhepheards are over us pag. <hi>127</hi>
               </item>
               <item>When through wicked ſhepheards thou art come to great miſerie pag. <hi>129</hi>
               </item>
               <item>When thou ſetteſt thy
<pb facs="tcp:150899:142"/>ſelfe to faſt pag. <hi>132</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou art railed upon for well doing pag. <hi>133</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou art perſecuted pag. <hi>134</hi>
               </item>
               <item>In partaking with Gods people in ſuffering pag. <hi>137</hi>
               </item>
               <item>When thou art called to defend the truth <hi>ib.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou wouldeſt bring forth ſeaſonable fruit for every eſtate pag. <hi>139</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou haſt children pag. <hi>141</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou wanteſt children pag. <hi>143</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If the Lord deny thee Children pag. <hi>145</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou wouldeſt have a comfortable and holy vſe of thy habitation. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:150899:142"/>
               <item>If thou wouldeſt have thy going out, and comming in bleſſed pag. <hi>147</hi>
               </item>
               <item>When thou eateſt or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyeſt any bleſsing that it may ſatisfie, and be ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied pag. <hi>148</hi>
               </item>
               <item>When thou takeſt thy reſt at night &amp;c. pag. <hi>150</hi>
               </item>
               <item>When thou putteſt thy hand to any worke pag. <hi>151</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou wouldeſt have thine outward bleſsings bleſſed pag. <hi>152</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou deſireſt to enjoy the labours of thine hands pag. <hi>154</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou art diligent in thy calling pag. <hi>155</hi>
               </item>
               <item>When thou ſeeſt wicked men follow unſatisfying
<pb facs="tcp:150899:143"/>things with reſtleſſe deſires, and thou deſireſt content. pag. <hi>156</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou feareſt thou ſhalt loſe by following the Lord pag. <hi>157</hi>
               </item>
               <item>When thou haſt loſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings by ſinne pag. <hi>159</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou feareſt loſſe of thy good name pag. <hi>160</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If the world deſpiſe thee &amp;c. pag. <hi>161</hi>
               </item>
               <item>When thou art in want for ſoule or body pag. <hi>163</hi>
               </item>
               <item>In liberall giving. pag. <hi>165</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If ſickneſſe be among us pag. <hi>168</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou feareſt death pag. <hi>170</hi>
               </item>
               <item>If thou feareſt untimely death pag. <hi>171</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:150899:143"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
